<document>
<h1>I</h1> 

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶1.01</margin>This is the [Hebrew] translation of the letter sent by the honorable attorney ʿAbbas b. Yefet Massouda, of blessed memory, in Arabic to the honorable <i>ḥakham</i>, the author, regarding the great urgency of publishing his essay, “The Writings of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>.” This was after he (= Massouda) had reviewed the essay while it was still in manuscript.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.02</margin>Cairo (may He keep it established forever) on the 21st day of the month of October, 1945.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.03</margin>Dear Honorable Chief Ḥakham Ṭoviyya Levi-Babovich:</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.04</margin>After inquiring about your peace and welfare, I have read with great interest the essay that Your Eminence has composed on ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>, and this offering was a veritable gift to me. I am amazed at the breadth of your knowledge about and the thoroughness of your research on Karaite history. I am overjoyed to see how Your Eminence always possesses the energy and wherewithal to search out every scrap of the priceless and rare works of our ancient sages that have not survived, with only a few of the scattered pages coming down to us as remnants. I hope that your tireless efforts in this regard will continue to bear fruit.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.05</margin>At the end of the essay, Your Eminence mentions the custom of the Karaites to recite, after the weekly Sabbath morning prayers, a special commemorative prayer for R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> and for the three sages from his camp: R. Ephraim, R. Elisha, and R. Ḥanukka.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.06</margin>By your leave, I request that you inform me of the history of these three sages, their works, and their opinions, so that I may know something of the past. You can rest assured, dear sir, that this request is neither the first nor will it be the last, as I shall continue to trouble Your Eminence many more times to slake my never-ending thirst for knowledge of the history of our singular ancestors.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.07</margin>In my opinion, we are obligated to publish these priceless essays and articles, so that every member of our community will be able to read them. It is also incumbent upon us to assemble them into a polished textbook that can be used for instruction in Karaite schools. This will greatly assist the further development of our community, awakening it from its collective slumber, which has gone on for too long.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.08</margin>Finally, I would like to express my heartfelt gratitude for this great gift, and please accept from your admirer his deepest respect.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.09</margin><i>ʿAbbas Massouda, Attorney at Law</i></p> 

<h1><margin side="right">¶1.10</margin>The Books of Our Karaite Sages Held in the Library of the Egyptian Karaite Community (Printed Editions and Manuscripts)</h1>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶1.11</margin>Since arriving in Egypt (June<footnote id="9">Babovich uses the Egyptian Arabic form of the month name, <i>yūniyū</i>.</footnote> 21, 1934), to all intents, my first undertaking pertaining to Karaite literature was to catalog in special catalogs all the spiritual riches possessed by our community, such as old Torah scrolls, works of our Karaite luminaries, and works of our Rabbanite brethren. These were heretofore haphazardly strewn in various corners of the [precincts of the] Religious Court.<footnote id="10">All Hebrew references to the <i>bet din</i>, which is translated as “Religious Court,” refer to the Karaite Religious Court in Cairo.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.12</margin>At the beginning of my venture, I decided to compile three different catalogs: in the first, I listed all the Torah scrolls, both new and ancient; in the second, I listed all the works authored by our Karaite sages; and in the third, [I listed] all the works of the sages of our Rabbanite brethren. All of these I recorded in Hebrew, of course, which is the language of our holy Torah, and in which, according to the sixth principle of the Ten Principles of our faith, every Karaite individual must be proficient.<footnote id="11">According to Ḥakham Judah Hadassi, a twelfth-century Karaite sage, the Ten Principles of Faith are (1) the belief in the uniqueness of God's creation and wisdom; (2) the belief that God is unequaled and incorporeal; (3) the belief that the world was created; (4) the knowledge of and reverence for God's Torah and the belief that God sent Moses and the other prophets; (5) the knowledge that the Torah is truth; (6) <u>the knowledge of the language of the Torah</u>; (7) the belief that the Temple in Jerusalem is God's palace; (8) the belief in the resurrection of the dead; (9) the belief that there will be judgment; and (10) the belief in reward and punishment (Judah Hadassi, <i>Eshkol ha-Kofer</i> [Gozlov, 1836], cols. 21c-d). For more on the Principles of Faith and other Karaite philosophy, see Daniel J. Lasker, <i>From Judah Hadassi to Elijah Bashyatsi, Studies in Late Medieval Karaite Philosophy</i> (Leiden: Brill, 2008), pp. 43ff. Eighteenth-century Karaite scholar Ḥakham Solomon b. Aaron briefly expounds upon these Ten Principles of Faith in <i>Appiryon ʿAsa Lo</i>, short version, chapter 16 (published in Adolf Neubauer, <i>Aus der Petersburger Bibliothek</i>, [Leipzig, 1866], Hebrew section, p. xvi). The Karaite Press republished this short version under the name <i>The Palanquin: On Karaite Practical Halakha</i> (Daly City, 2017).</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.13</margin>To our great misfortune, despite the fact that it is one of the principles of our faith, very few of the learned men of the community are properly proficient in this language; though almost all members of the community know how to read and pray in it, this is merely like the chirping of birds.<footnote id="12">This expression, “like the chirping of birds,” was previously used to describe the thoughtless prayers of the common people in <i>Appiryon ʿAsa Lo</i>; see <i>The Palanquin</i>, p. 101. Cf. Isaiah 8:19, which uses the word <i>meẓafẓefim</i> (the word translated here as “chirping”) to refer to the idolatrous utterances of soothsayers.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.14</margin>But we should find some consolation in the fact that, although deficient in their knowledge of Hebrew, the members of the community are keen to know the quantity and quality of the great spiritual wealth that we have in our hands, especially in regards to the literature composed by our sages of blessed memory. They are eager to know: Who were these sages? When and where did they live? What is the content of their works, and what is their value?—and so on.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.15</margin>At the head of this group is none other than my dear friend ʿAbbas b. Yefet Massouda, the respected attorney and member in good standing of our National Committee. He is also the author of a dissertation entitled <i>A Contribution to the Study of the Waqf in Egyptian Law</i> (<i>Contribution à l'étude du Wakf en droit égyptien,</i> by the lawyer A.Y. Massouda, Paris 1925, and in Arabic, <i>Ṣāḥib al-Risālat</i> “<i>Al</i>-<i>ʾAwqāf al-ʾIslāmiyya fī Miṣr</i>”). His Honor is dear in my eyes, and I have expended much effort to fulfill his wishes, in keeping with what the sages of blessed memory<footnote id="13">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya is paraphrasing a Rabbinic text (cf. Mishna, <i>Avot</i> 2:4). It is not clear whether Ḥakham Ṭoviyya was familiar with the paraphrase of the Mishna from Karaite or Rabbanite sources or was directly paraphrasing the Mishna itself. He attributes the text to <i>Ḥazal</i>, an acronym for “our sages of blessed memory.” This is the typical term used by Rabbanite Jews to refer to the rabbis of the Mishna and Talmud. Among some Karaite authors, such as the late-seventeenth-century Mordecai b. Nisan, it is used to refer to deceased Karaite rabbis. (See Mordecai b. Nisan, <i>Royal Attire: On Karaite and Rabbanite Beliefs</i>, trans. and ed. Gabriel Wasserman [Daly City: the Karaite Press, 2016], p. 45, note 46.) Because we do not know Ḥakham Ṭoviyya's source for the quote, we have translated the initial <i>ḥet</i> in <i>Ḥazal</i> as “the sages” instead of “our sages.”</footnote> said: “Annul your own will in favor of your fellows', so that they will annul theirs in favor of your own.” From time to time, when time permits, I will compose a short article dedicated to each and every one of our sages whose book or books can be found in the library of the Religious Court. I shall publish them for the edification of the members of our community and for the benefit of the general public.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.16</margin>[I should] note here that when I embarked upon this task of creating a catalog of our sages' works, I did not content myself with merely recording the title of a given work, its author, and the year in which it was written; rather, I also appended some biographical details and comments for the reader's benefit, so that these books should not be impenetrable to readers at first glance. Now, [when bringing this book to publication,] I have added more details about these works and their respective authors, as far as my knowledge extends.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.17</margin>We shall begin at the beginning by discussing the works of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, the man of God and Exilarch who laid the foundation for our religion, Karaism.<footnote id="14">As described below, Ḥakham Ṭoviyya does not intend to convey that ʿAnan <i>founded</i> the Karaite movement out of whole cloth. Rather, like many Karaites, he understood ʿAnan to be the individual who helped jump-start what became a unified Karaite movement in the following centuries. It is important to reflect on ʿAnan's reception by later Karaites, as they were not of one mind about him. Some Karaites found him to be too close to Rabbinic tradition, which he purportedly opposed; for instance, he accepted exclusively Rabbinic principles of hermeneutics. As Marina Rustow writes: “Indeed, medieval sources speak of ʿAnanites as an independent group that existed separate from the Karaites well into the tenth century. However, his (= Anan's) measure of esteem among virtually all Karaites is highly understandable in light of the fact that he was the first notable Jewish figure who openly declared his opposition to the Rabbinic establishment. For this alone, he was offered pride of place in the chain of Karaite scholarly tradition” (Rustow, <i>Scripture and Schism, Samaritan and Karaite Treasures from the Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary</i> [New York: Jewish Theological Seminary of America, 2000], pp. 64f.).</footnote></p>

<h1><margin side="right">¶1.18</margin>About R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi (May God's Mercy Be Upon Him)</h1>

<p>(This essay was composed in tribute to my dear friend, the honorable attorney ʿAbbas Massouda, may his light shine, son of Yefet of blessed memory.)</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.19</margin>R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi (715–811 CE) lived in the Near East, perhaps in Persia, and moved from there to Babylonia, to the city of Baghdad. In those days, there were two great academies in Babylonia: one in the city of Sura and the other in Pumbedita. The standard practice [of that period] in Babylonia (that is, the country of Iraq) was that the heads of each of these two academies would appoint the new Exilarch,<footnote id="15">The post of Exilarch stretches back to antiquity. During various periods in history, the Exilarch wielded considerable clout and was granted varying degrees of sovereign powers over his constituency by the Muslim ruler. According to tradition, the Exilarchate was established in ancient Babylon, where the Jews were exiled from Jerusalem in the sixth century BCE. Its first occupant was said to be Shealtiel, the son of the deposed Judean monarch, Jehoiachin. While the seat of the Exilarchate was in Iraq, it eventually branched out to other parts of the Near East, including Syria, Palestine, and Egypt. (See Jacob Mann, “The Exilarchal Office in Babylonia, and Its Branching Out at the End of the Gaonic Period” [Hebrew], in <i>Livre d'hommage à la mémoire du Dr. Samuel Poznański</i>, Hebrew section [Warsaw, 1927], pp. 18–32.) By the twelfth century, various Jewish leaders—Rabbanite and Karaite alike—called for the abolition of the post, which they felt was anachronistic and a source of schism; for instance, the Rabbanite Head of the Academy in Baghdad, Samuel b. Eli (twelfth century), was a vociferous critic of it. (See Arnold E. Franklin, <i>This Noble House: Jewish Descendants of King David in the Medieval Islamic East</i> [Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2013], p. 127.) According to Eliezer Bashan's article in the <i>Encyclopaedia Judaica</i>, an outside hand finally brought the Exilarchate to an end in the fifteenth century, when it was abolished by the Mongol emperor Tamerlane (Eliezer Bashan [Sternberg], “Exilarch,” in <i>Encyclopaedia Judaica</i>, 2nd ed. [Detroit and elsewhere: Thomson-Gale, 2007], vol. 6, p. 607); however, we have found no earlier source for this claim. In any event, families that could prove descent from the Exilarchs and the House of David continued to be regarded in high esteem in their respective communities; to this day, some of these families still exist in both Karaite and Rabbanite circles and are aware of their origins (see, for example, Nadine Epstein, “King David's Genes,” <i>Moment Magazine</i>, March-April, 2012 <url>http://www.momentmag.com/king-davids-genes-2</url>). Among contemporary Karaites, descendants of the Karaite Exilarchs are known by their surname “Alnassi” (“al-Nasi”) (personal communication with Yaron Lalouz, c. 2013, during which he also remarked that he had a student from the Alnassi family who prided himself on his descent from ʿAnan).</footnote> who was known in Aramaic as the <i>resh galuta</i>,<footnote id="16">Literally, “head of the Exile,” which is also the literal meaning of English “Exilarch” and Hebrew <i>rosh ha-gola</i>. The Jewish community of Babylonia was founded by exiles from the Land of Israel at the time of the destruction of the First Temple and thus was known as “the Exile.”</footnote> and the caliph would ratify and uphold their appointment. Customarily, the Exilarch had to be descended from the family of King David (peace be upon him), King of Judah, and the position of Exilarch was passed down from father to son. When the Exilarch Solomon ha-Nasi died with no male heir, it was expected that the mantle of leadership would be passed on to the eldest son of his deceased brother David, ʿAnan ha-Nasi; it was his prerogative to inherit the vacant seat of the Exilarch. However, the heads of these two academies balked and refused to appoint ʿAnan, for they knew that he opposed the Oral Law;<footnote id="17">Regarding ʿAnan, it is evident from his surviving work that he was well versed in both Scripture and Rabbinic law and exegesis. See Rustow, <i>Scripture and Schism</i>, p. 65: “[H]e at some point relinquished his commitment to the Rabbinic system, choosing instead to derive Jewish law from the Bible. He also used the Prophets and Hagiographa as sources of law on a par with Torah itself, a technical innovation that would have a profound effect on subsequent Karaite law and exegesis. All of this resulted in a code that inevitably deviated from many of the laws recorded in the Mishna and the Talmud.”</footnote> instead, they appointed his brother Ḥananiah (or Josiah, according to the scholar Abraham Harkavy<footnote id="18">Abraham Elijah Harkavy (1835–1919) was a historian, orientalist, and bibliographer who was born in Russia to a family of prominent, traditional Rabbanite Jews. He studied in the famed Volozhin Yeshiva in his youth before turning his efforts to authoring works on the history of the Near East and publishing newly discovered manuscripts. In 1872, he was given the respected position of head librarian at the Imperial Library in St. Petersburg, which gave him access to a treasure trove of hitherto unknown or lost manuscripts, including the Firkovich Collections. His work, and its importance for the first modern study of Karaitica, cannot be emphasized enough. (See Herman Rosenthal, “Harkavy, Albert,” in <i>The Jewish Encyclopaedia</i>, vol. 6, pp. 230f.; Abraham N. Poliak, “Harkavy, Albert,” in <i>Encyclopaedia Judaica</i>, 1st ed. [Jerusalem and New York, 1972], vol. 7, column 1339ff.)</footnote>), who was younger and less wise than he. Nevertheless, those who preferred the candidacy of ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>, and were of the same mind as him, appointed him as Exilarch over them.<footnote id="19">Here Babovich seeks to avoid the oft-repeated myth that ʿAnan invented the Karaite movement out of spite for being passed over for the post of Exilarch. (For this myth, see, for example, Abraham Ibn Daud, <i>The Book of Tradition (Sefer ha-Qabbalah)</i>, trans. and ed. Gerson D. Cohen [Philadelphia: Jewish Publication Society of America, 1967], pp. 48ff. [annotated English], 37f. [Hebrew]). Babovich clearly concurs with the vast majority of modern-day scholars, who see absolutely no causal relation between ʿAnan's rejection for the Exilarchate and the purported invention of the Karaite movement.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.20</margin>This is not the place to elaborate on the discord and controversy surrounding the appointment of the Exilarch—how R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>, through the machinations of his opponents, was thrown into prison and sentenced to be hanged on a Friday; how he made a pact with and became a close friend and confidant of a giant in the Islamic world, the “high priest” Abu Nuʿman ibn Thabit Abu Ḥanifa,<footnote id="20">Born Numan ibn Thabit ibn Zuta ibn Marzuban (699–767) in Kufa, Iraq, he was the founder of the Sunni Hanafi school of <i>fiqh</i> (Islamic jurisprudence). He would not fare as well as ʿAnan; according to Arab chroniclers, he died in prison.</footnote> also an innocent man of impeccable integrity who was imprisoned as a result of his detractors; how this great man provided invaluable advice to R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>, as it is written: <i>And the noble counseled noble things, and he for noble things rises up</i><footnote id="21">New American Standard Bible translation, which fits the context.</footnote> (Isaiah 32:8); how through that counsel, R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> was able to gain an audience with the caliph, Abu Jaʿfar al-Mansur;<footnote id="22">He lived 714–775 and was considered the founder of the Abbasid Caliphate.</footnote> and how the caliph accepted his defense, found him innocent, and absolved him of all wrongdoing in the year 4521–4522 from Creation, which corresponds to 761–762 CE, and appointed him Exilarch over his own group of followers. Anyone interested in learning more about these events should see the work that I published in 1913 when I was in Sevastopol, Russia. The name of that work is <i>Ẓemiḥat Dat ha-Qaraʾim</i>. Here, however, I would like to focus solely on the literary legacy that R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> left behind.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.21</margin>Nonetheless, I must mention here that R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> traveled to Jerusalem (may it be rebuilt and established) toward the end of his life, along with most of his followers,<footnote id="23">Modern scholars do not accept the historicity of ʿAnan's move to Jerusalem or the establishment of a Karaite community there in his time. See Judith Olszowy-Schlanger, <i>Karaite Marriage Documents from the Cairo Geniza</i> (Leiden: Brill, 1997), p. 48: “The historical value of this legend has been rejected by modern scholars, all the more so since it is not confirmed in early Karaite sources. On the contrary, these sources describe the Karaism of ʿAnan and of Benjamin al-Nahāwendī as a purely Babylonian phenomenon.” As Olszowy-Schlanger notes there, Salmon b. Yeruḥam writes in his commentary on the Psalms that Karaites began to settle in Jerusalem only after the time of Nahawandi; that is, in the second half of the ninth century. See Lawrence Marwick (ed.), <i>The Arabic Commentary of Salmon b. Yeruḥam the Karaite on the Book of Psalms, Chapters 42–72</i> (Philadelphia: Dropsie College, 1956), p. 98.</footnote> and there built the ancient Karaite synagogue, which we have discussed in the newspaper “<i>Kalīm</i>” (an Arabic word, meaning “the one who speaks with God”—which is how Arabic speakers describe our teacher Moses, peace be upon him), Year 1, June 1945, in the eighth issue published by our community's youth [division]. There, they (= ʿAnan and his followers) abstained from the consumption of meat and the drinking of wine [and] mourned and wept for the destruction of the Temple. R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi passed away there in 811 CE and was buried among the graves at the foot of Mount Moriah, near the tomb of the prophet Zechariah (peace be upon him). (See <i>Bené Reshef</i> [Vienna, 1871], p. 17: “The text of the letter sent from the holy city of Jerusalem to the learned R. Tobias b. R. Moses the Mourner, peace be upon him, in the community of Constantinople” written by David ha-Nasi b. Boʿaz ha-Nasi, a descendant of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>, in 1009 CE.)</p>

<p>These mourners called themselves “the Mourners of Zion and Jerusalem” and also <i>the men that sigh and that cry</i> (Ezekiel 9:4). They abstained from wine and meat in Jerusalem for two reasons: first, as a sign of mourning for the destruction of Jerusalem and the Temple; and second, because they were of the opinion that the consumption of meat and the drinking of wine were forbidden ever since the day that sacrifices ceased to be offered, along with wine libations over these sacrifices, on the brass altar (see Exodus 29:39–40).</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.22</margin>It is not farfetched to assume that while ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> was in Jerusalem, he also went to Egypt; indeed, there is such a tradition among the Egyptian Karaites.<footnote id="24">While it is entirely possible that ʿAnan visited Egypt at some point in his life, it is clear that by the tenth century, the Karaite Exilarchs, from the seed of ʿAnan, were firmly established in Jerusalem. In addition, it is interesting to note that one branch of ʿAnan's descendants actually headed the Rabbanite Yeshiva in Jerusalem. (See Moshe Gil, <i>A History of Palestine</i> [New York: Cambridge University Press, 1999], pp. 658, 782–84, and 790.)</footnote> [This seems] especially [likely] if we keep in mind that he made it his life's mission to spread the faith of Karaism throughout the world. [If so], he established the Karaite community here<footnote id="25">Whenever Ḥakham Ṭoviyya says “here,” he means Egypt or Cairo in particular.</footnote> on solid foundations, and therefore the Karaite community in Egypt can be rightfully considered one of the oldest Karaite communities in the world.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.23</margin>Let us return to the topic at hand. Although R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> doubtlessly left behind many works, as many who came after him attested, the vast majority of them have been lost to posterity, and only three of them are known to us by name. They are (1) <i>The Book of Commandments</i>; (2) a commentary on the Pentateuch; and (3) <i>Sefer Fadhlaka</i><footnote id="26"><i>Fadhlaka</i> has the meaning of “statement” or “abstract.”</footnote><i>—“</i>a condensed explanation.” Even these three books, whose names we do know, were thought lost, until the late renowned scholar Abraham Harkavy, while on a visit to Egypt in the year [5]646<footnote id="27">The author writes 646 followed by the abbreviation <i>lpʺq</i>, which means <i>li-peraṭ qaṭan</i>, indicating the year without the millennium.</footnote> (1886), discovered six folios<footnote id="28">That is, leaves of paper or parchment; if both sides of each folio contain writing, this comes out to 12 pages.</footnote> from the<i> Book of Commandments</i> of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>.</p>

<p>Later, he had the fortuitous opportunity<footnote id="29">The verb form <i>hiqra</i> is in the <i>hifʿil</i> conjugation. This form of this root usually refers to active, typically divine, causation of happenstance; however, here, it might simply be a flowery way of saying “it happened.” For someone who believes in divine control of happenstance in general, there is not much difference between these two readings.</footnote> to purchase many additional folios from the Egyptian <i>genizot</i><footnote id="30">A <i>geniza</i> is a storeroom, often located in a synagogue, in which materials bearing God's name (and often just Hebrew script) are disposed. The most famous of these is, of course, the Cairo Geniza; see below in ¶3.13, footnote 21.</footnote> and discovered among them two more loose leaves and, thereafter, eight more loose leaves from the <i>Book of Commandments</i>. He eventually consolidated all these into one work, which he published in 1903 in St. Petersburg (may God protect it, Amen), along with other fragmentary remnants of the books of commandments by our Karaite sages R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi and R. Daniel al-Qumisi. He had found them among the books of the Imperial Library in the capital city of St. Petersburg, which had originally been brought there by the great researcher Abraham Firkovich (may his soul rest in Eden). The scholar Abraham Elijah Harkavy published this entire collection in his book <i>Zikhron la-Rishonim</i>, volume 8, under the name “Second Part of the Book <i>Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i> by R. Simḥa Pinsker: <i>On the History and Literature of the Karaite Faith</i>,”<footnote id="31">The complex title of this book by Harkavy reflects the fact that the author intended it to serve double duty in two separate series. On the one hand, it is the eighth volume of Harkavy's own series <i>Zikhron la-Rishonim</i> on literature from the period of the Geonim (Jewish scholars in roughly eighth- to eleventh-century Babylonia), and it is included in printings of this series. On the other hand, even though Harkavy published this book several decades after Pinsker's death, he intended it to also be a second volume of Pinsker's <i>Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i> (see following footnote); indeed, subsequent printings of <i>Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i>, such as the Jerusalem 1968 printing, include Harkavy's book as the final volume.</footnote> which the aforementioned scholar Simḥa Pinsker<footnote id="32">Simḥa Pinsker (1801–1864), a Jewish historian and archaeologist, was born in Tarnopol, Galicia (today in southern Poland) to a prominent family of Ḥasidic Jews. His studies and travels eventually took him to the cosmopolitan city of Odessa, Ukraine, where he ingratiated himself into the society of <i>maskilim</i> (Jewish intellectuals) there. He also began to do extensive research into Jewish history, examining and eventually publishing manuscripts that he acquired from the famed Karaite scholar Abraham Firkovich. In 1860, he published his multivolume work<i> Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i> on the history and literature of the Karaites.</footnote> had written and published in Vienna in 1860. Harkavy's publication was financed by a noted wealthy Karaite from the city of Ekaterinoslav,<footnote id="33">Modern Dnipropetrovsk (officially Dnipro), Ukraine.</footnote> Elijah b. Joseph Gigit (of blessed memory), as an act of kindness and beneficence. This edition can be found in the library of our Religious Court in two pieces.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.24</margin>R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> apparently composed most of his works in Aramaic, which was the language in use among the Karaite sages of his time. Aramaic is the language in which he also wrote his works: (1) the commentary on the Torah and (2) the <i>Fadhlaka</i>. Scholars are in disagreement as to the contents of the latter, but it very likely comprised a digest of incest laws,<footnote id="34">Known in Hebrew as <i>rikkuv</i>, literally, “grafting,” this catenary theory of forbidden marriages was based on a Karaite interpretation of the verse about husband and wife “becoming one flesh” (Genesis 2:24). As a result, early Karaites believed all relatives by marriage took on the status of blood relatives. Under this school of thought, the pool of prospective mates for Karaites shrank substantially. This principle was not accepted by later Karaite scholars. See<i> The Palanquin</i>, p. 155, and below in ¶2.18, footnote 20.</footnote> which appeared in greater detail in his book on the commandments, and this <i>Book of Commandments</i> was likewise written in Aramaic.</p>

<p>When the scholar Abraham Harkavy published these fragments, he translated them into Hebrew and printed them alongside the Aramaic. In addition, in order to give interested readers an understanding of the external appearance of these fragments, he included three facsimile copies from three different manuscripts and reproduced them in three pages at the beginning of the book. (A “facsimile” is a manuscript that is printed by means of drawing with light, which is called “photography,” in accordance with the appearance and dimensions [of the original manuscript].)<footnote id="35">Interestingly, Ḥakham Ṭoviyya still felt the need to explain what a facsimile is in the middle of the twentieth century.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.25</margin>In the aforementioned fragments, R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi discusses forbidden foods; the laws of <i>shaʿaṭnez</i> (forbidden mixtures of wool and linen); tzitzith; the laws of the Sabbatical Year and the Jubilee; the laws of honoring the Torah and the commandments; the laws of blemishes;<footnote id="36">The Hebrew word <i>mum</i> refers to blemishes that render a person or animal unfit for ritual purposes.</footnote> the laws of reading the Torah; the laws of benedictions over food; the laws of Torah study; the laws of maintaining purity and attending the synagogue;<footnote id="37">Maintaining ritual purity while attending synagogue was not exclusive to Karaite and ʿAnanite thought. In medieval <i>Ashkenaz</i> and <i>Ẓarfat</i> (Franco-Germany), menstruating women were barred from entering the synagogue. By the same token, men who had experienced a seminal emission were strongly discouraged from entering the synagogue until ritually cleansed. See Jeffrey R. Wolf, “The Synagogue in Medieval Franco-Germany: Between Perception and Law” (Hebrew), in <i>Kenishta: Studies of the Synagogue World</i> 2 (2003), pp. 19–24; Elisheva Baumgarten, “`And they do nicely': A Reappraisal of Menstruating Women's Refusal to Enter the Sanctuary in Medieval Ashkenaz” (Hebrew), in <i>Ta Shma: Studies in Judaica in Memory of Israel M. Ta-Shma</i> (Alon Shvut: Tevunot Press, 2011), volume 1, pp. 85–104.</footnote> the laws of the four individuals who are required to make the Thanksgiving Blessing; the laws of reading the Torah Portions; the laws of purity and impurity and of vermin; the laws of the Sabbath and the Festivals; the laws of circumcision; the laws of women and forbidden relations; and the laws of inheritance. All these laws are missing either their beginnings or ends, all in the state in which they were rescued from the ravages of time and destruction. I say “destruction” because the people who disagreed with the opinions of ʿAnan ha-Nasi (that is, his opponents) used to obliterate his works, as is related by the Rabbanite sage Yashar Reggio,<footnote id="38">Isaac Samuel Reggio of Gorizia (1784–1855), an Austro-Italian scholar and rabbi.</footnote> may his soul rest in Eden (see his <i>Sefer ha-Tora ve-ha-Pilosofiya</i>, note to p. 118).<footnote id="39">It is interesting to note that the first Rabbanite to mount a serious challenge to ʿAnan's <i>Book of Commandment</i>s was the noted Saʿadya Gaʾon, who devoted an entire treatise to refuting it, which is now completely lost (see Rustow, <i>Scripture and Schism</i>, p. 70). It is perhaps one of the ironies of history that the Rabbanites are generally considered the victor in the disputes between Rabbanites and Karaites, yet Saʿadya's <i>Book of Refutations of ʿAnan</i> has been lost, and a significant portion of ʿAnan's <i>Book of Commandments</i> is still extant. In the following centuries, many Karaite sages took aim at the extreme positions advocated by Saʿadya Gaʾon. See Samuel Poznański, <i>The Karaite Literary Opponents of Saadiah Gaon</i> (Princeton, 1908).</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.26</margin>I now would like to take the opportunity to tell you [an experience that occurred to me] in 1927, when I traveled to the capital, St. Petersburg, now known as “Leningrad”; at the time, I was living in the city of Sevastopol on the Crimean Peninsula. I remained there (= St. Petersburg), for 40 days, from May 1 to June 10. The aim of my trip was to glean information about the discoveries of the late great scholar Abraham Firkovich (of blessed memory) kept at the Imperial Library, which he had discovered when visiting various places in Europe, Asia, and Africa. While I was in St. Petersburg, it came to my attention that my longtime dear friend, the Russian scholar Sokolov,<footnote id="40">The author never mentions Sokolov's first name, but this appears to be M.N. Sokolov.</footnote> an expert in ancient languages and especially in Hebrew, was working in the Asiatic Museum<footnote id="41">The Asiatic Museum in St. Petersburg was founded in 1818 by the Russian Academy of Sciences, as a collection of “Eastern medals, manuscripts, and books.” It existed as an independent institution until 1930, when it was absorbed into the new Institute of Oriental Studies. (Irina F. Popova, “History of the Institute of Oriental Manuscripts,” <url>http://www.orientalstudies.ru/eng/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=46&amp;Itemid=82</url>, retrieved on February 27, 2017.)</footnote> and had experienced a stroke of good fortune, for he too had come across a fragment from the <i>Book of Commandments</i>, aside from the fragments that had been published by Harkavy. The majority of this fragment contains laws of incest, written in Aramaic. He presented this discovery, in Russian translation and accompanied by his own notes, to a conference of distinguished scholars, headed by the renowned, top scholar Pavel Kokovtsov.<footnote id="42">Pavel Kokovtsov (1861–1942) was a professor of Hebrew at St. Petersburg University. For an overview of his life and scholarship, see Moshe Perlmann, “Kokovstov, Paul Konstantinovich,” <i>Encyclopaedia Judaica</i>, 1st ed., vol. 10, cols. 1157f.</footnote> My friend accorded me respect by extending a personal invitation to attend the presentation. I, along with two good friends from the Karaite community in St. Petersburg, went to the lecture, and we listened to the important give-and-take that took place regarding this newly discovered fragment. At the conclusion of the presentation, the great scholar Kokovtsov delivered a short lecture on R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, fittingly<footnote id="43">This translation assumes that the Hebrew should be vocalized <i>ba-ashuro</i>, along the lines of the much more common adverb of the same meaning <i>la-ashuro</i>. It can perhaps be vocalized <i>be-ishuro</i>, according to which, the line would read “fine and wise words of approbation.”</footnote> fine and wise words. May all who recognize and speak the truth be blessed, Amen.</p>

<quotation><margin side="right">¶1.26.1</margin>It would not be excessive for us to mention here that the linguist Sokolov, who is mentioned above in the body of the text, is a student of the famous linguist Pavel Kokovtsov, likewise mentioned above, and Kokovtsov [in turn] was a student of the late famous scholar Daniel b. Abraham Chwolson, who worked a great deal on the discoveries of the great scholar Abraham Firkovich and wrote two important works on the gravestones in the Karaite cemeteries of the Crimean Peninsula. These inscriptions hold particular importance for Karaite history [but also] for general knowledge. There are three Karaite cemeteries in Crimea famous for their antiquity: i) in Chufut-Kale, which is near Bakhchysarai—the modern capital of the Tatars; ii) in the city of Mangup; and iii) in Solchat—the old Tatar capital, which is currently called “Aski Krim”—literally, “old Crimea.” These gravestones had sunk deep in the earth on account of the heaviness of the stones and the passage of time; many of them date back 1,000 years, and some nearly 2,000. Abraham Firkovich excavated these graveyards and literally brought them (= the gravestones) to light;<footnote id="44">The Hebrew verb <i>le-hotzi la-or</i> usually means “to publish,” but here, Ḥakham Ṭoviyya underscores that it also retains its literal meaning “to bring to light.”</footnote> therefore, scholars rightfully consider Abraham Firkovich to be the father of the study of ancient Crimean history.

I would like to take this opportunity to clarify something for my esteemed readers, who might find it strange that I have dated these cemeteries to nearly two millennia ago, while I myself have written in this essay that the Karaite faith arose only in the years 761–762. The answer is that Karaites did indeed arrive on the Crimean Peninsula more than 2,000 years ago, along with the army of King Cyrus of Persia and his son Cambyses, but in those days they were known [simply] as the “Israelites,” for the term “Karaites” did not yet exist. Their first settlement was Kale, which is built on a tall hill, and that is the very reason these Israelites desired it when they came with the army of Cyrus and Cambyses and seized it. These Israelites had never heard anything of the Oral Law, which was authored in the second century CE in the Land of Israel and called [the] “Mishna.” They (that is, the Israelites in Crimea) faithfully conducted themselves<footnote id="45">Cf. Proverbs 28:6.</footnote> on the exclusive basis of the Torah written by our master Moses (peace be upon him) and the Holy Scriptures. Only in the mid-ninth century (that is, 100 years after the Karaite faith arose in Babylonia), did Karaite emissaries come tell them all that had happened in Babylonia, and how R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi had denied the Oral Law and based himself only on the Written Law, and that those who followed him called themselves “Scripturalists” or “Karaites,” in order to distinguish themselves from the believers in the Oral Law. At that point, the Israelites who lived in the fortress at Kale, and in other locations in Crimea, declared that R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> was right, and they agreed to base themselves only on the Written Law; they, too, began referring to themselves as “Karaites” or “Scripturalists.” Thus, one can understand that we have attributed the ancient cemeteries in the Crimean Peninsula [to Karaites], on the basis of later developments. Whosoever is interested in a more extensive explanation of this subject should read my second work <i>Sheloshet he-ʿAlim</i>, which I published in Sevastopol, Russia in 1926.</quotation>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.27</margin>When I left Simferopol, on the Crimean Peninsula, where I had been exiled—<i>although there [was] no violence in my hands, and my prayer [was] pure</i> (Job 16:17)<footnote id="46">JPS translation.</footnote>—and arrived in Egypt, [then], in the first years of my stay here, I searched here with the Lamp of Diogenes,<footnote id="47">That is, “I searched very thoroughly.” Diogenes of Sinope was an ancient Greek philosopher, who is said to have carried around a lamp during the day because he was “looking for a[n honest] man.” (See Diogenes Laertius, <i>Lives of Eminent Philosophers</i>, trans. R. D. Hicks, Loeb Classical Library [London: William Heinemann Ltd., 1925, second printing 1931], Book 6, §42, p. 42.)</footnote> hoping that I, too, would experience good fortune and find the missing sections from R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi's <i>Book of Commandments</i> as well as the rest of his writings. To my great dismay, I have been unable so far to find anything pertinent. Perhaps one day I will have more success in finding them, and we will have the aforementioned <i>Book of Commandments</i> in full, in all its beauty and splendor. Who knows? Perhaps the missing pieces from the <i>Book of Commandments</i> are hiding in the house of someone in the community, awaiting the next Abraham Firkovich. If only the members of our community would open up their concealed archives, so that we followers of Firkovich could be fortunate to publish them, bringing glory to our nation and benefitting all. May it be His will, Amen!</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.28</margin>In order to edify the interested reader, I will cite here some excerpts from extant passages of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi's commentary on the commandments of the Torah:</p>

<quotation><margin side="right">¶1.29</margin>1. R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> made it an established principle to determine the new month according to sight [of the moon] with the naked eye, in accordance with the ancient practice, and not according to [a system of] calculation.<footnote id="48">A lunar month consists of either 29 or 30 days. By convention, a month of 29 days is considered “deficient,” and a month of 30 days is considered “full.” In antiquity, a new month was declared when the crescent new moon was visible to observers. To this day, some observant Karaite Jews still sight the new moon to declare the new month; see the next footnote.</footnote> Currently, Karaites establish it according to possibility of sight, which would accord with physical sight. In other words, they make a calculation in advance, and if the calculation indicates that the new moon has a possibility of being sighted on the horizon after sunset, assuming that it is not obstructed by clouds, then they establish the morrow as the New Moon (= the beginning of the new month) and consider the preceding month deficient (that is, consisting of 29 days); they do not make an effort to [wait and] see the new moon above the horizon with their own eyes. If, however, their calculation concludes that it is impossible to sight the moon with the naked eye because its light is too dim, then even if the skies are clear, they consider the preceding month full (that is, consisting of 30 days), and they establish the New Moon on the day <i>after</i> the morrow.

<margin side="right">¶1.30</margin>2. He also established that the Festival of Matzah (= Passover) should be observed [at a time] according to the presence of the <i>aviv</i> in the Land of Israel as is prescribed by our holy Torah and not according to a calculation.<footnote id="49">The Festival of Matzah falls in the first month of the biblical calendar, which is the first month after the barley reaches the state of <i>aviv</i>. There is no prescribed number of months in the biblical calendar. A year has either 12 or 13 months. By convention, a year with 12 months is considered a regular year, and a year with 13 months is considered a leap year. If, during the twelfth month, the barley is at a stage of ripening called <i>aviv</i> (see Exodus 9:31, Deuteronomy 16:1, et passim), then the year is considered complete, and there is no thirteenth month—the next New Moon signals the first month of the new year. If the barley is not yet <i>aviv</i>, then an extra lunar cycle is added, and the new year occurs a month later. Here, Ḥakham Ṭoviyya explains how the Karaites of his day were setting the new year without directly observing the stage of barley ripening. According to the Rabbinic tradition, there are seven leap years interspersed throughout a 19-year cycle.</footnote> Currently, Karaites also use a calculation for this matter, which aligns with the presence of the <i>aviv</i> in the Land of Israel. The system works as follows: for every nineteen years, which they call a “minor lunar cycle,” they make seven leap years of 13 months and 12 regular years of 12 months. This is the order: [years] 1, 2, 4, 5, 7, 9, 10, 12, 13, 15, 16, and 18 are all regular, while 3, 6, 8, 11, 14, 17, and 19 are all leap years. It is done in this manner because it is exceedingly difficult for Karaites, who are now scattered across the globe, to find out about the <i>aviv</i> in the Land of Israel every year.<footnote id="50">In contrast to the state of affairs regarding the <i>aviv</i> described by Ḥakham Ṭoviyya, several centuries prior to him, the Karaites in the areas near the Land of Israel would carry out <i>aviv</i> searches each year. See Mordecai b. Nisan<i>, Royal Attire</i>, pp. 167–168.</footnote> The Karaites also say that [the use of] this calculation was established by the “goodly figs”<footnote id="51">Cf. Jeremiah 24:2. See further below, ¶3.51.</footnote>—Jewish sages exiled to Babylonia after the destruction of the First Temple—to use when they were distanced from the Land of Israel. The inventor of this calculation was the Greek scholar Meton.<footnote id="52">Meton (Athens, fifth century BCE) was a mathematician and astronomer. He is best known for calculations involving the eponymous 19-year Metonic cycle, which he introduced into the so-called lunisolar Attic calendar. The Metonic calendar incorporates knowledge that 19 solar years and 235 lunar months are very nearly equal, such that lunar periods repeat on the same day of the year as 19 years previous. See Robert Hannah, <i>Greek and Roman Calendars</i> (Bristol Classical Press, 2005), pp. 52–71.</footnote>

<margin side="right">¶1.31</margin>3. He ruled that the Festival of Shavuot should always be observed on a Sunday, as it is written in the Torah: <i>And ye shall count unto you from the morrow after the Sabbath, from the day that ye brought the sheaf of the waving; seven Sabbaths shall there be complete; even unto the morrow after the seventh Sabbath shall ye number 50 days …</i> (Leviticus 23:15–16).<footnote id="53">Adapted from the JPS translation, with changes to reflect the Karaite understanding of the verse.</footnote> He refused to accept the explanation of those who say that one must interpret the words <i>the morrow after the Sabbath</i> here as meaning “the morrow after the holiday,”<footnote id="54">The standard Rabbanite interpretation is as follows: the word <i>Sabbath</i> refers to the first day of Passover, and, thus, the counting begins on the second day of Passover, “the morrow after the <i>Sabbath</i>,” and Shavuot is observed 49 days after that. See, for example, Babylonian Talmud, <i>Menaḥot</i> 65b.</footnote> since we do not find [anywhere] in the Torah that the Sabbath is referred to as a “holiday.”<footnote id="55">The phraseology here seems to be reversed; Ḥakham Ṭoviyya means to say that a holiday is never called “the Sabbath” in the Torah, whereas his text says that the Sabbath is never called a “holiday” in the Torah. That said, word order in Hebrew is looser and allows for the subject to come last. In any case, his intent is clear.</footnote>

<margin side="right">¶1.32</margin>4. In the passage: <i>If brethren dwell together, and one of them die, and have no child, the wife of the dead shall not be married abroad unto one not of his kin; her husband's brother shall go in unto her, and take her to him to wife, and perform the duty of a husband's brother unto her. And it shall be, that the firstborn that she beareth shall succeed in the name of his brother that is dead, that his name be not blotted out of Israel</i> (Deuteronomy 25:5–6), he interpreted the word <i>brethren</i> as meaning “close relatives” [instead of biological brothers]. For how can we say that the Torah here permits a man [to marry] his brother's wife, when the Torah itself utterly forbids this, when it says:<i> Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy brother's wife: it is thy brother's nakedness</i> (Leviticus 18:16).

<margin side="right">¶1.33</margin>5. R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> ruled that matzah must be made from barley, because the words <i>leḥem ʿoni,</i> as matzah is called in the Torah (Deuteronomy 16:3), fit two different interpretations: (a) <i>leḥem ʿoni</i>—we can interpret it as “bread of affliction,” that is, bread that our ancestors ate in remembrance of the fact that they were afflicted under Egyptian rule for 210 years;<footnote id="56">Although Genesis 15:13 and Exodus 12:40 state, respectively, that the Israelites spent 400 or 430 years in Egypt, these numbers create a chronological problem when compared to the lifespans of the descendants of Levi in Exodus 6:18–20, 7:7. Kohath was alive when the Israelites entered Egypt (Genesis 46:11), and he lived 133 years. His son Amram lived 137. Amram's son, Moses, was 80 years old in the year of the Exodus. These numbers add up to only 350 years, and presumably there was significant overlap between the lifespans of the fathers and the sons, so the total should be far less. Therefore, the early Rabbanite chronographic work <i>Seder ʿOlam</i> calculates that the 400 years began with the birth of Isaac and that the Israelites spent only 210 of these years actually in Egypt. See <i>Seder ʿOlam</i>, ed. Chaim Milikowsky (Jerusalem: Yad Ben-Zvi, 2013), volume 1, p. 226 (ch. 3), and Milikowsky's discussion in volume 2, pp. 55ff. This figure of 210 years is very widely accepted by later Rabbanite writers, and, evidently, was also taken for granted by Ḥakham Ṭoviyya.</footnote> (b) <i>leḥem ʿoni</i>—we can interpret it as “bread of the poor and destitute,” that is, bread that is generally consumed by the poor and destitute because of its low cost. Such bread is made from barley because they cannot afford to buy bread made from wheat, which is an expensive bread. However, our subsequent sages (of blessed memory) permitted all types of grain for making matzah, namely, [the following] six: (a) wheat, (b) <i>kussemet</i>, (c) barley, (d) <i>shibbolet shuʿal</i>, (e) <i>shifon</i>, and (f) millet<footnote id="57">Aside from the sixth item (millet), this list of grains that can be used to make matzah is identical to the one in Mishna, <i>Pesaḥim</i> 2:5. Two of the names—<i>ḥiṭṭa</i> (wheat) and <i>seʿora</i> (barley)—are clear, but the identification of the remaining three is controversial. Zohar Amar has written an entire book on the subject (from a Rabbanite-Talmudic, but scientific, point of view): <i>Five Types of Grain: Historical, Halachic, and Conceptual Aspects</i> (Hebrew; Mechon Har Bracha, 2011).</footnote> (see the book <i>Adderet</i> [<i>Eliyyahu</i>], Seder Ḥag ha-Maẓẓot, Chapter 5). Currently, Karaites make their matzah from wheat, and they say that because the eating of matzah is a commandment and because one must accord the commandments great respect, they make it from the more expensive grain—wheat.<footnote id="58">Incidentally, it is worth noting that in the first decades of the twentieth century, the Egyptian government supplied both the Karaite and Rabbanite communities with fine wheat for the production of matzah. This practice was maintained even during World War II, when ordinary commodities were hard to come by. The production of the bread was jointly supervised by representatives of both communities, and each issued its respective seal of approval on the finished product; see Yosef Algamil, <i>Karaite Jewry in Egypt in Modern Times</i> (Ramla: National Council of Karaite Jews in Israel, 1985), English section, p. 15.</footnote>

<margin side="right">¶1.34</margin>6. He prohibited sexual relations on the Sabbath, on account of what is written in the Torah: <i>Six days thou shalt work, but on the seventh day thou shalt rest; in plowing time and in harvest thou shalt rest</i> (Exodus 34:21). He draws a comparison between plowing and sexual intercourse and permits [the latter] only on weekdays and solely for the purpose of procreation. Therefore, he [also] forbids sexual intercourse with a pregnant woman. And to those who counter with the verse,<i> and call the Sabbath a delight</i> (Isaiah 58:13), the Karaite sages retort that sexual intercourse [on the Sabbath] leads to weariness and affliction,<footnote id="59">This is a pun on the anagrams (words with identical letters, in different orders) <i>negaʿ</i>, “affliction,” and <i>ʿoneg</i>, “delight” (which already appears in the early medieval work <i>Sefer Yeẓira</i>). The word used here for “weariness,” <i>yegaʿ</i>, in turn, rhymes with <i>negaʿ</i>.</footnote> rather than <i>delight</i>.<footnote id="60">Refraining from sexual intercourse on the Sabbath was not a Karaite innovation. Other non-Rabbinic communities likewise prohibited it, such as the Beta Israel of Ethiopia; see the document “Tĕʾĕzāza Sanbat” in <i>Falasha Anthology</i>, ed. and trans. Wolf Leslau (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1951), p. 19. The Beta Israel treat the <i>Book of Jubilees</i> as canonical; this work, from the Second Temple Era, explicitly forbids marital relations on the Sabbath in 50:8: “And the man that does any work on it (the Sabbath) shall die: whoever desecrates that day, whoever lies with (his) wife […] shall die” (R.H. Charles, ed. <i>The Apocrypha and Pseudepigrapha of the Old Testament in English</i>, volume II: Pseudepigrapha [Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1913], pp. 81f.). In addition, Samaritans, at least in recent centuries, have refrained from sexual intercourse on the Sabbath; see Bernhard Beer, <i>Das Buch der Jubiläen und sein Verhältniss zu den Midraschim</i> (Leipzig: Wolfgang Gerhard, 1856), p. 54, though he notes that Zacharias Frankel believed that this was a later development that Samaritans learned from Karaite Jews. By contrast, the Rabbis of the Talmud recommend the Sabbath as the ideal time for conjugal relations (Babylonian Talmud, <i>Ketubbot</i> 62b). This may have been a reactionary measure against groups that prohibited such activity on the Sabbath. This would not be the only Rabbanite ruling instituted as a reaction to Karaite halakha; as another example, many scholars believe that the Rabbanite custom dating to the Geonic period of reciting a blessing before lighting lamps or candles late on Friday afternoon, to provide light during the Sabbath, began as a reaction to the prevalent Karaite view prohibiting the kindling of such lights. (See, for example, Yitzhak D. Gilat, <i>Studies in the Development of the Halakha</i> [Hebrew; Bar-Ilan University Press, 1992], p. 344.)</footnote>

<margin side="right">¶1.35</margin>7. He opposed with all his might the system of calculations of postponements established by our Rabbanite brethren,<footnote id="61">The Rabbanites have rules to postpone the celebration of the New Moon by a day if the calculated date will cause certain holidays to fall on certain days of the week. These rules do not appear explicitly in the Talmud, though some vague references to a primitive form of some of them occur in the Babylonian Talmud, <i>Rosh ha-Shana</i> 20a. The formulation cited here is in §428 of the law codes <i>Ṭur</i> and <i>Shulḥan ʿArukh</i>. The <i>Ṭur</i> was written in the fourteenth century, and the <i>Shulḥan ʿArukh</i> in the sixteenth, but these rules predate the <i>Ṭur</i> by several hundred years, though they are post-Talmudic.</footnote> who say, for instance, that Passover can never fall on Monday, Wednesday, or Friday;<footnote id="62">The days of the week here are all indicated by acronyms. For example, the first acronym is <i>BaD”U</i>; that is, Passover may not begin on Monday (the second day of the week, <i>bet</i>), Wednesday (the fourth day of the week, <i>dalet</i>), or Friday (the sixth day of the week, <i>vav</i>). Our author alludes ironically to this acronym when he uses the word “fabricated,” <i>badu</i>, later in the sentence, which is also an allusion to I Kings 12:33: <i>And [Jeroboam] went up unto the altar which he had made in Beth-el on the fifteenth day in the eighth month, even in the month which he had devised [bada] of his own heart […].</i></footnote> that <i>ʿAẓeret</i> (= Shavuot) can never fall on Tuesday, Thursday, or Saturday; that Rosh Hashanah can never fall on Sunday, Wednesday, or Friday; that Yom Kippur can never fall on Sunday, Tuesday, or Friday; and that Pur[im] can never fall on Saturday, Monday, or Wednesday. He said that all these are not from the Torah but were fabricated by the sages.</quotation>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶1.36</margin>Now, from the remnants and relics<footnote id="63">Cf. Joshua 8:22.</footnote> that we have from R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi's own writings, and from all that later sages—be they followers or opponents—wrote about him, and from the history of the development of the Karaite faith,<footnote id="64">Early Karaite history is still very unclear. As Zvi Cahn has written: “The origin and development of the Karaites are still largely surrounded by mystery and not a little uncertainty…This uncertainty is due to the lack of the historic sense that characterized the Karaites, though they have produced hundreds of books (and even thousands according to their assertions) that have been lost in the course of time” (<i>The Rise of the Karaite Sect: A New Light on the Halakah and Origin of the Karaites</i> [New York: M. Tausner, 1937], p. 37). The various traditions about ʿAnan, who he was, where and when he lived, and whether or not he was the Exilarch or even of the family of the Exilarchate, are all rooted in reports, some of them contradictory, from hundreds of years later. See Moshe Gil, “Karaite Antiquities” (Hebrew), in <i>Teʿuda</i> 15 (1999), pp. 71–107; and idem, “The Origins of the Karaites,” in Meira Polliack (ed.), <i>Karaite Judaism: A Guide to Its History and Literary Sources</i> (Leiden: Brill, 2003), pp. 73–118.</footnote> [one thing] is clear as day: the fundamental basis on which he built Karaism is the Written Torah itself, without resorting to an Oral Law that contains the words of sages. The motto of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi was always: “Search Scripture well, and do not rely on my opinion” (<i>ḥappisu be-oraita shappir, ve-ʾal tishaʿanu ʿal daʿti</i>).<footnote id="65">This aphorism's first clause is in Aramaic, and the second clause—influenced by Proverbs 3:5—is in Hebrew. Its origin is shrouded in uncertainty, but its first extant citation is in the commentary of Yefet b. ʿEli to the book of Zechariah. Its origin was possibly in the (now lost) introduction to ʿAnan's <i>Book of Commandments</i>.</footnote> However, in regard to matters that do not have clear answers in the Torah, he allowed utilizing the hermeneutical principle of <i>heqqesh</i> (inference); for instance, <i>heqqesh qal va-ḥomer</i> (<i>argumentum a fortiori</i>, reasoning from the stronger case to the weaker case); <i>heqqesh dimyon</i> (analogical reasoning); or<i> gezera shava</i> (reasoning on the basis of similar language), and others. This is because he was of the opinion that all that is derived by <i>heqqesh</i> from the Torah is considered as if it were actually written in the Torah itself. The scholars say that on this point, R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi followed the path of the aforementioned Abu Ḥanifa, who likewise utilized inferences of <i>dimyon</i> and <i>qal va-ḥomer</i> in his explication of the Holy Qurʾan.<footnote id="66">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya uses the abbreviation <i>quf</i>, which apparently stands for <i>qadosh</i>, “holy.” One might be surprised to see a Jewish sage use this epithet for the Qurʾan, but it is less surprising given the ecumenical activities of Ḥakham Ṭoviyya. As noted in the introduction, prominent Muslims attended his funeral or expressed condolences.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.37</margin>However, in those places where one cannot find answers, neither in the Torah nor via the hermeneutical methods, R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> would command [his followers] to conduct themselves in the way of “the Burden of Inheritance” (<i>sevel yerusha</i>); that is, to conduct themselves in accordance with the custom that the people had observed since ancient times, provided that the custom not contravene the spirit of the Torah.<footnote id="67">In its most narrow sense, the Burden of Inheritance refers to customs and practices that were known at the time the Torah was given and were incorporated by reference in the Torah. For example, we read in Genesis 37:31 that Joseph's brothers slaughtered (from the Hebrew root for <i>sheḥita</i>) a goat. From this Karaites derive that (i) the proper way to slaughter was known to ancient Israelites and (ii) the Torah did not need to specify a particular method. This also explains why Karaites do not believe an Oral Torah was necessary to explain how to slaughter.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.38</margin>And from all this, we can conclude that the Karaite faith is based on three main pillars, namely: (i) the written word (that is, all that is written in the Torah); (ii) the [hermeneutical principle of] <i>heqqesh</i>; and (iii) the Burden of Inheritance.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.39</margin>It is important to realize that the principle of freedom of interpretation, as laid down by ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>, soon bore fruit: immediately after him, there arose distinguished scholars among the Karaites, in every single field of scholarship known at the time. They were the first to establish the study of philology and linguistics; they devised the pointing system (<i>niqqud</i>) and established the Tiberian [system of] pointing;<footnote id="68">Hebrew, like most other Semitic languages, was originally written as a consonantal skeleton without accompanying signs for the vowels. At some point in the second half of the first millennium CE, various schools of Jewish scholars known as “Masoretes” arose, most famously in Tiberias in the Galilee but also elsewhere. They invented the system of pointing, the diacritical marks indicating vowels, to record the reading traditions of the Bible, which had hitherto been preserved orally. They also worked on preserving other aspects of the biblical text, such as the exact spelling. Though Ḥakham Ṭoviyya writes here that the inventors of the pointing system were Karaites, there is no way to prove this; in fact, both Karaites and Rabbanites were heavily involved in Masoretic activity and shared their work with one another. See Geoffrey Khan, “The Karaites and the Hebrew Bible,” lecture at the Fifteenth International Orion Symposium, “The Texts of the Bible from the Dead Sea Scrolls to the Biblical Manuscripts of the Vienna Papyrus Collection,” April 10, 2016, <url>https://www.scribd.com/document/329693162/KHAN-GEOFFREY-15-OrSymp-2016-the-Karaites-and-the-Hebrew-Bible</url>, retrieved on March 30, 2017.</footnote> they compiled lexicons;<footnote id="69">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya uses the word <i>egron</i> for “lexicon.” This word was invented by the Rabbanite scholar R. Saʿadya Gaʾon, as a calque of the Arabic <i>jamhara</i>, “collection”; Saʿadya's word <i>egron</i> is from the Hebrew root <i>ʾ-g-r</i>, “to collect.” See Neḥemya Allony (ed.), <i>Ha-Egron: Kitāb ʾUṣūl al-Shiʿr al-ʿIbrānī</i> (Hebrew; Jerusalem: Academy of the Hebrew Language, 1969), pp. 17f. and 87f.; on 17f., Allony lists six later works that used Saʿadya's term <i>egron</i> as part of their title, at least one of which is by a Karaite author, ʿAli b. Suleiman.</footnote> [and] they invented the study of comparative linguistics, [comparing] Hebrew, Aramaic and Arabic. They introduced meter and rhyme into [Hebrew] poetry, in the style of the Arabic poets.<footnote id="70">In fact, Karaite poets were not the originators of either rhyme or syllabic meter in Hebrew poetry, as Ḥakham Ṭoviyya implies here with the word <i>makhnisim</i>, “introduced.” Rhyme was used in Hebrew poetry starting with the great Rabbanite poets of the sixth century CE, such as Yannai, long before the time of ʿAnan, and it has been present in most Hebrew poetry since. (See Ezra Fleischer, “<i>Beḥinnot be-Tahalikh ʿAliyyat he-Ḥaruz ba-Shira ha-ʿIvrit ha-Qeduma</i>,” <i>Meḥqeré Yerushalayim be-Sifrut ʿIvrit</i> 1 [1981], pp. 226–238.) On the other hand, syllabic meters, in the style of the Arabic poets, were introduced into Hebrew poetry in the tenth century by Dunash b. Labraṭ, who was a student of the great Rabbanite scholar and poet Saʿadya Gaʾon. (See Jefim Schirmann and Ezra Fleischer, <i>The History of Hebrew Poetry in Muslim Spain</i> [Hebrew; Jerusalem: Magnes Press and Ben-Zvi Institute, 1995], pp. 119–122.) Babovich is not the first to make the claim that Karaite poets preceded Dunash in using such meters in Hebrew; Simḥa Pinsker stated this in his <i>Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i> (Vienna: Adalbert della Torre, 1860), p. 4, without any real evidence. This is probably related to Pinsker's misdating of R. Moses Darʿi to the mid-ninth century rather than the mid-twelfth; see Joachim Yeshaya, <i>Medieval Hebrew Poetry in Muslim Egypt:</i><i> The Secular Poetry of the Karaite Poet Moses b. Abraham Darʿī</i> (Leiden: Brill, 2011), pp. 11f. Babovich was familiar with Pinsker's work, and in this very paragraph, he quotes a passage from the same page, so he presumably also obtained this idea from him (and, as we will see below, in ¶1.45, he follow Pinsker's dating of R. Moses Darʿi to the ninth century). In any event, later Karaite poets certainly used syllabic meters and rhyme in their Hebrew poetry.</footnote> They also produced great poets, great exegetes, distinguished theologians,<footnote id="71">The term for divinity (<i>elohut</i>, or <i>elohi</i>) is often used in Hebrew writing of the past millennium in reference to the work of theologians, even non-Jewish ones, and later on, to kabbalists as well. See Yaakov Shmuel Spiegel, <i>ʿAmmudim be-Toledot ha-Sefer ha-ʿIvri</i>, vol. 3 (Jerusalem, 2014), pp. 149–154.</footnote> expert physicians, and more.<footnote id="72">Note that the Hebrew text continues with the following sentences, but the Arabic text of the original publication of <i>Rosh Pinna</i> ends this paragraph here. The omitted text appears in the original Arabic publication of <i>Rosh Pinna</i> in what we have designated as paragraph 1.51. In order to harmonize the Arabic and Hebrew, we have moved the Arabic text to paragraph 1.39 in our edition.</footnote> All of this bears testimony to the fact that the Karaite faith is not the source of stagnation and ossification that its detractors, in their antipathy to Karaism, make it out to be, but rather the opposite is true: it is a source of progress and innovation.<footnote id="73">This is not the only place where Ḥakham Ṭoviyya writes adamantly about this point. He writes similarly in the introduction to his halakhic work, <i>Ḥuqqé ha-Peraṭ la-ʿAdat ha-Qaraʾim be-Miẓrayim</i>: “Our lips will grow weary if we continue to demonstrate that the favorite dictum of the founder of our community, R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>, `Search Scripture well, and do not rely on my opinion,' shows with certainty that Karaism is based on free thinking and is not a source of archaism and unyielding rigidity, as is claimed by those who are hostile to Karaism. On the contrary, it is a source of development, and it leaves great space for progress, in accordance with the place and time.” Babovich did not succeed in publishing this work in his lifetime; after his death, it was found among his papers by Yosef Algamil, who published it in his collection of Babovich's writings, <i>Pirqé Ṭoviyya</i>, vol. 2, pp. 253–349. Our quote appears on p. 264. For the story of Algamil's discovery of the work, see p. 273, footnote 1.</footnote></p>

<p>And thus wrote the great scholar of Karaite literature, Simḥa Pinsker (may his soul rest in Eden), in his acclaimed <i>Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i> (p. 4): “We have discovered that there were Karaite authors who toiled in this vast field, sowing, reaping, and giving forth fruit in all fields of external knowledge:<footnote id="74">The term “external knowledge” probably means here, as it often does in Hebrew literature, secular branches of scholarship.</footnote> astronomy, philosophy, rhetoric, poetry, philology, and lexicography,<footnote id="75">Literally, “arranging Hebrew roots alphabetically.”</footnote> as they needed to do in order to understand the plain words of Scripture and their meanings.”</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.40</margin>So that what I have said not remain abstract, I think that it would be proper here to name some of the more distinguished Karaite scholars who excelled in the various fields mentioned above. [I will limit this list] exclusively to the names of the earlier ones, [who flourished up until] the fifteenth century; if I have the leisure, and it is an opportune time, with God's help, I will make an effort to write another work on Karaite literature in general, in which I will enumerate the names of all the Karaite sages, from antiquity to the present, the well known and the obscure. But right now I will content myself with mentioning only the names of a few distinguished early Karaite sages, namely, the following:</p>

<quotation>I. <margin side="right">¶1.41</margin><sc>Philologists:</sc> Judah b. Quraysh from Fez (ninth century);<footnote id="76">I have retained Ḥakham Ṭoviyya's designation of which centuries these scholars lived; however, it would behoove the reader to independently verify some of these dates, as subsequent scholarship has clarified the correct time frames.</footnote> Abu al-Faraj Aaron, who is known as “the grammarian from Jerusalem” (tenth century); Judah b. ʿAlan of Tiberias (tenth century) (according to R. Simḥa Pinsker, he is to be identified with Yaḥya b. [rather, Abu] Zakariya the Writer, who is mentioned in Arabic by the Arab writer Masʿudi ʿAli Abu ʾl-Ḥasan, who died in 926).

II. <margin side="right">¶1.42</margin><sc>Rhetoricians:</sc> R. Salmon b. Yeruḥim (tenth century);<footnote id="77">Here, Ḥakham Ṭoviyya makes reference to the Karaite sage known as “Salmon b. Yeruḥam” or “Salomon b. Yeruḥim.” Salmon's most notable achievement is his polemic against R. Saʿadya Gaʾon, entitled <i>Sefer Milḥamot Adonai</i> (<i>The Book of the Wars of the Lord</i>), which has been edited and published by Israel Davidson (New York: Jewish Theological Seminary of America, 1934).</footnote> R. Nissi b. Noah (tenth century); R. Sahl b. Maẓliaḥ ha-Kohen, who is called “Abu Sari” (tenth century); R. Ḥasun b. Maẓliaḥ the Caller<footnote id="78">The Hebrew ha-Qoré (or possibly ha-Qara) apparently indicates that this sage actively called upon his fellow Jews to take action, possibly by returning to the land of Israel or by returning to the Torah.</footnote> (tenth century); R. Tobias ha-ʿOved (eleventh century); and R. Moses ha-Kohani (eleventh century).

III. <margin side="right">¶1.43</margin><sc>Inventors of the Tiberian Vocalization System:</sc> Ben Asher (tenth century);<footnote id="79">There was a large Ben Asher family of Masoretes, of whom the most famous was Aaron Ben Asher. Much ink has been spilled over the question of whether they were Karaites or Rabbanites. See Khan, “The Karaites and the Hebrew Bible” (above in ¶1.39, footnote 61), who cites some of the scholarly literature on the topic. Evidently, Ḥakham Ṭoviyya believed that they were Karaites. Raphael Zer takes the position that the Masorete of the Aleppo Codex was indeed a Karaite, but his article on the topic remains agnostic on whether the Masorete was Aaron Ben Asher. See Raphael Zer, “Was the Masorete of the Aleppo Codex Rabbinical or Karaite?” (Hebrew), <i>Sefunot</i> N.S. 8 (23), (2003), pp. 573–587 and “Was the Masorete of the Aleppo Codex of Rabbanite or of Karaite Origin?” <i>Textus</i> 24 (2009) pp. 239–262.</footnote> Rav Muḥa (tenth century) and his son Moses b. Muḥa (eleventh century); and Judah b. Moses the Vocalizer of the East b. Judah ha-Gibbor (tenth century?).

IV. <margin side="right">¶1.44</margin><sc>Lexicographers:</sc> David b. Abraham al-Fasi (tenth century); Menaḥem b. Saruq<footnote id="80">Standard scholarship has always numbered Menaḥem b. Saruq among the Rabbanites, so it is surprising to see Babovich list him here. The evolution of this claim is as follows. The famous Rabbanite scholar Samuel David Luzzatto (known as “Shadal,” 1800–1865) theorizes, in his article “Menaḥem b. Saruq and Ḥasdai b. Isaac” (Hebrew) (in Luzzatto, <i>Bet ha-Oẓar</i> [Lemberg: Eva Grossmann, 1847], folio 33b) that Menaḥem's antagonist Ḥasdai persecuted him because Ḥasdai suspected him of being a Karaite. Luzzatto writes that suspicions of Saruq's Karaism were floating around in the nineteenth century, and he deduces from a close reading of Menaḥem's epistle to Ḥasdai that this was Ḥasdai's accusation against Menaḥem. However, Luzzatto writes that these suspicions were utterly unfounded (ibid., folio 34b). Nonetheless, Pinsker (<i>Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i>, p. 168) adopts Luzzatto's theory but says that the suspicions were correct that Menaḥem did, indeed, hold some Karaite views in his heart, though he was socially part of the Rabbanite community and prayed in the Rabbanite synagogues. As we have seen above (¶1.23, ¶1.39), Babovich owed a great debt to Pinsker's work and considered it historically reliable, so this must be the source of his odd inclusion of Menaḥem in this list of important Karaites.</footnote> (eleventh century); ʿAli b. Suleiman (eleventh century).

V. <margin side="right">¶1.45</margin><sc>Major Poets:</sc> R. Moses Darʿi (ninth century);<footnote id="81">The works of Moses Darʿi have recently been published in critical editions by Joachim Yeshaya: <i>Medieval Hebrew Poetry</i> and <i>Poetry and Memory in Karaite Prayer:</i><i> The Liturgical Poetry of the Karaite Poet Moses b. Abraham Darʿī</i> (Leiden: Brill, 2014). In 1934, none other than Ḥakham Ṭoviyya Babovich named a synagogue in Cairo, which had been built in the 1920s, after Moses Darʿi; this attests to the ongoing importance of this medieval figure to the leaders of the modern Karaite community (Yeshaya, <i>Medieval Poetry</i>, p. 51). Modern scholarship dates Moses Darʿi to the mid-twelfth century, not the mid-ninth; see above in ¶1.39, footnote 63.</footnote> Mevorakh b. Nathan b. Nisan ha-Levi (ninth century); Adonim b. R. Mesiman ha-Levi and his son R. Moses (ninth century); R. Judah b. ʿAlan of Tiberias (tenth century); Israel ha-Dayyan<footnote id="82">A judge in a religious court.</footnote> I of Alexandria b. R. Daniel ha-Maʿaravi (eleventh century); R. Caleb Afendopolo (fifteenth century).

VI. <margin side="right">¶1.46</margin><sc>Major Expositors of the Bible:</sc> R. Daniel b. Moses al-Qumisi or Damaghani (ninth century); R. Yefet the Great Teacher (tenth century); R. Joseph b. Noah (eleventh century); R. Jacob b. Reuben (eleventh century); R. Aaron I the Physician b. Joseph (thirteenth century); R. Aaron the Younger b. Elijah of Nicomedia (fourteenth century).

VII. <margin side="right">¶1.47</margin><sc>Major Expositors of the Commandments</sc>: R. Daniel b. Moses al-Qumisi or Damaghani (ninth century); R. Levi ha-Levi, who is called “Abu Hashim” b. R. Yefet the Great Teacher (tenth century); R. Yeshuʿa b. Judah, who is known as “Abu al-Faraj Furqan Abu Asad” (eleventh century) and his disciple Ibn Taras, from Castile in Spain (eleventh century).<footnote id="83">According to the twelfth-century Rabbanite historian Abraham ibn Daud, this Ibn Taras did not start out as a Karaite but was won over to Karaism by Yeshuʿa. (See Ibn Daud, <i>The Book of Tradition</i>, pp. 94ff.)</footnote> (Regarding the latter, it is related that his wife was a learned woman, and after his death, the members of the community would turn to her with any queries about religion, and they would listen to her as one listens to a prophet of God. She was famously known among them as “the [female] teacher”—<i>al-Muʿallima</i> in Arabic.)<footnote id="84">The sentence regarding <i>al-Muʿallima</i> appears in a footnote in the original Arabic publication of <i>Rosh Pinna</i>. In order to harmonize the Arabic and Hebrew, we have moved the footnote into the main Arabic text of paragraph 1.47 in our edition.</footnote> R. Judah Hadassi (twelfth century); R. Israel ha-Dayyan II b. Samuel ha-Maʿaravi<footnote id="85">The Karaite Press has published a translation of R. Israel ha-Dayyan's treatises on slaughter and the principles of faith, together with a critical edition of the Judeo-Arabic. (See <i>The Karaite Creed and Discourse on Slaughter</i>, ed. Raphael Dascalu, trans. Raphael Dascalu and James Walker [Daly City: The Karaite Press], 2018.)</footnote> and his disciple R. Yefet the Physician b. David b. Samuel b. Ẓaʿir (thirteenth century); R. Samuel ha-Maʿaravi (fourteenth century); and R. Elijah Bašyachi (fifteenth century).

VIII. <margin side="right">¶1.48</margin><sc>Medical Scholars:</sc> R. Moses Darʿi (ninth century); Abu Bayan al-Mudabbir, whose Hebrew name was Solomon b. Israel, and who was personal physician to Sultan Saladin the Ayyubid (twelfth century) and his son Abu Fadl Daʾud, whose Hebrew name was David b. Solomon (twelfth century). (The latter composed several treatises on medicine, one of the most famous of which is <i>The Rules of Medicinal Compounds</i> (in Arabic: <i>Dustūr al-Adwiyya al-Murakkaba</i>). This manuscript is currently held by the library in Oxford, England, and [also] in the city of Munich, Germany,<footnote id="86">The author uses the French name for Germany, “Allemagne.”</footnote> as well as here in Cairo. He was personal physician to the Sultan al-Malik al-Abil Abu Bakr bin al-Ayyub.<footnote id="87">Known more simply as “Al-Adil I” or “Sayf al-Din” (1145–1218), he was the younger brother and successor to Saladin.</footnote> The renowned Arab physician Ibn Abu Usibiyya, who composed the long <i>History of Physicians</i>, was his pupil and colleague.)<footnote id="88">The words beginning with “The latter” through “pupil and colleague” appear in a footnote in the original Arabic publication of <i>Rosh Pinna</i>. In order to harmonize the Arabic and Hebrew, we have moved the footnote into the main Arabic text of paragraph 1.48 in our edition.</footnote> R. Aaron I the Physician b. Joseph (thirteenth century); R. Yefet the Physician b. David b. Samuel b. Ẓaʿir, who is called “al-Ḥakim al-Ṣafī” (thirteenth century); and R. Elijah Bašyachi (fifteenth century).

IX. <margin side="right">¶1.49</margin><sc>Theologians:</sc> R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi (ninth century); R. Menaḥem Niẓani ha-Golé b. Michael (ninth century); David b. Marwan of Babylon-Iraq, who is known as “al-Muqammiṣ” (ninth century);<footnote id="89">Although many Karaites have considered al-Muqqamiṣ to be Karaite, we have no evidence that al-Muqqamiṣ was affiliated with either the Karaites or the Rabbanites. Indeed, al-Qirqisani, the famed tenth-century Karaite, in his <i>Kitāb al-Anwār wa-al-Marāqib</i>, simply refers to al-Muqqamiṣ as a Jew.</footnote> R. Joseph the Seer b. Abraham, known as “Joseph al-Baṣir”<footnote id="90">He was known euphemistically as “the Seer” (ha-Roʾé) because he was blind; his substantial writings (including several polemics, one against the Samaritan sanctification of Mount Gerizim and another against Islam, as well as responsa) were written via dictation. Al-Baṣir was born in Basra, Iraq and later moved to Jerusalem, where he studied at the academy of Joseph ibn Nuḥ. (See Marina Rustow, <i>Scripture and Schism</i>, p. 75.)</footnote> (he was an Israelite<footnote id="91">That is, an ordinary Jew, of neither priestly nor Levitical descent.</footnote> and not, as some scholars have mistakenly written, a priest) (eleventh century); R. Aaron the Latter of Nicomedia (fourteenth century).

X. <margin side="right">¶1.50</margin><sc>Historiographers of Jewish Religious Sects:</sc> Jacob b. Isaac b. Shemaya al-Qirqisani, who is called “Abu Yusuf Yaʿqub” (tenth century), was unique in that he wrote histories, for it was not generally customary among our early sages to engage in this particular endeavor. This teacher of ours, Jacob al-Qirqisani ([from] Qirqisān, a place near Baghdad), was also a great religious scholar and a great exegete. He composed all his works in Arabic; the most notable of them is his work <i>Kitāb</i> <i>al-Anwār wa-al-Marāqib</i> (<i>The Book of Lights and Watchtowers</i>) in 13 parts.<footnote id="92">One of the foremost scholars of Karaitica, Leon Nemoy (1901–1997) published this monumental work in Arabic (New York: Alexander Kohut Memorial Foundation, 1939–1943). A properly translated and annotated edition remains a scholarly desideratum.</footnote>

XI. <margin side="right">¶1.51</margin><sc>Enumerators of the Karaite Sages:</sc> Ibn al-Hiti (fifteenth century) authored a work in Arabic in which he lists the names of all the Karaite sages. The last is R. Samuel the Physician b. Moses ha-Maʿaravi, the author of the <i>Book of Commandments</i>, which is called <i>al-Murshīd</i> and in Hebrew<i> Ha-Meyasher</i> (“the one that makes straight”), which he wrote in the year 5194 from Creation, which corresponds to 1434 CE. Ibn al-Hiti's book was published by the scholar Margoliouth in London in 1897.<footnote id="93">He refers to the orientalist George Margoliouth (1853–1924), who edited and published the work as “Ibn al-Hītī's Arabic Chronicle of Karaite Doctors,” <i>Jewish Quarterly Review</i> IX (1897): pp. 429ff.</footnote></quotation>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶1.52</margin>I would like to record here for posterity the words of the excellent Arab historian Taqi al-Din Aḥmad ibn ʿAli Maqrizi (fourteenth century), who mentions R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi. These are they (as translated [into Hebrew] by R. Simḥa Pinsker):</p>

<quotation>Whereas the ʿAnanites originate with ʿAnan the Exilarch, who came from the east in the days of Abu Jaʿfar al-Manṣur, bringing with him a copy of Deuteronomy that had been copied from the autograph of Moses the Prophet (peace be upon him). And when he saw how the Jews—both Karaites and Rabbanites alike—stood up to oppose him and what was in his hands, he mustered singular strength to stand up to them and dispute them about their religion. They respected him and considered him a descendant of King David (peace be upon him), a man who was exceedingly pious in matters of religion. They believed that had he lived in the times of the Temple, he would have been a prophet. Nobody dared to act arrogantly against him, because, besides what we have mentioned, he was also held in high esteem by the caliph, who accorded him great honor. What differentiated him from the [other] Jews was his establishment of the calendar according to the sighting of the new moon, as it is also in Islam; he did not care what day of the week the New Moon fell on. He abandoned the calculations of the Rabbanites and their system of leap years, maintaining that they were mistaken in this; he [instead] relied solely on the appearance of the barley grain.</quotation>

<p indent="no">(See the second volume of his book <i>al-Khuṭaṭ</i> [<i>The Paths</i>], the chapter entitled “Contemporary Jewish Sects.”)</p>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶1.53</margin>It is important to note here that what al-Maqrizi said about both Rabbanites and Karaites being opposed to “what was in his hands” is true. Some early Karaites opposed ʿAnan on some matters; in other words, they did not agree with him on everything, but all [these disagreements] related only to the branches and not to the roots, for they were all in agreement with him regarding the main tenets of the movement.<footnote id="94">The Hebrew word here is <i>dat</i>, which often means the legalistic aspects of religion. Here, however, it appears to mean “sect,” or in modern parlance, “movement.”</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.54</margin>It should also be noted here that in the days of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, his adherents were called “ʿAnanites”; it was only with the passage of time that they took for themselves the name “Scripturalists” or “Karaites.” And from this it is clear that the terms “ʿAnanites,” “Scripturalists,” and “Karaites,” which we find in the literature, are all synonyms.<footnote id="95">At some point, these terms might have been synonymous, but at least in the tenth century, the ʿAnanites and Karaites were two distinct groups. See Marina Rustow, <i>Heresy and the Politics of Community, The Jews of the Fatimid Caliphate</i> (Ithaca and London: Cornell University Press, 2008), pp. 53ff. The epigraph page at the beginning of Rustow's book contains an English translation of a quote from Qirqisani's <i>Kitāb al-Anwār wa-al-Marāqib</i>, Book I, 10:1: “[Some of the disagreements between the Iraqi and Palestinian Rabbanites] make each group accuse the other of heresy. In fact, the religious divergence between the two groups is no smaller than that between both of them on the one hand and the Qaraites and the ʿAnanites on the other” (brackets in the original).</footnote></p> 

<p><margin side="right">¶1.55</margin>On every Sabbath, in every Karaite synagogue, a special commemorative prayer is recited for R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> following the morning prayers.<footnote id="98">This custom continues to this day in Karaite synagogues throughout Israel.</footnote> This is its text:</p>

<quotation>May our God and the God of our forefathers have mercy on our dead, on your dead, and on the dead of the entire nation of the House of Israel. First and foremost, in memory of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, man of God, the Exilarch, who opened the way of the Torah, and illuminated the eyes of the Karaites, and held back many from sin and iniquity,<footnote id="96">Cf. Malachi 2:6.</footnote> and led us on a straight path.<footnote id="97">Cf. Psalms 107:7.</footnote> May the God of Israel repose him in a good resting place, in a lovely resting place, in a dignified resting place, along with the righteous, who inherit Paradise. And may the verse that is written be fulfilled upon him: <i>And it shall come to pass in that day, that the root of Jesse, that standeth for an ensign of the peoples, unto him shall the nations seek; and his resting place shall be glorious</i> (Isaiah 11:10). <i>His enemies will I clothe with shame; But upon himself shall his crown shine</i> (Psalms 132:18). And may the verse that is written also be fulfilled upon him: <i>But go thou thy way till the end be; and thou shalt rest, and shalt stand up to thy lot, at the end of the days</i> (Daniel 12:13).</quotation>

<p><margin side="right">¶1.56</margin>After this [prayer], they recite a memorial prayer for three [other] sages, who were teachers of the earlier Karaites and helped him (= ʿAnan) spread the Karaite faith around the world: R. Ephraim, R. Elisha, and R. Ḥanukka,<footnote id="99">The reader will recall that Ḥakham Ṭoviyya was specifically requested to expound upon these three obscure individuals. He gives us no information about them, and, indeed, not much is known. See also Abraham Baer Gottlober, <i>Biqqoret le-Toledot ha-Qaraʾim</i> (Vilna, 1864), pp. 113, 124, 129, 139.</footnote> may their merits protect us, Amen.</p>

<p><i>Ḥakham Ṭoviyya b. Simḥa (of blessed memory) Levi-Babovich</i></p>

<h1>II An Article on R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi (Ninth Century CE)</h1>

<p>By: Ḥakham Ṭoviyya b. Simḥa Levi-Babovich</p>

<p>Cairo, Egypt</p>

<p>1947</p>

<h1><margin side="right">¶2.01</margin>II R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi b. Moses (Ninth Century CE)</h1> 

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶2.02</margin>Now, it came to pass after the death of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>,<footnote id="100">Cf. Joshua 1:1.</footnote> the man of God and Exilarch, that his son Saul ha-Nasi inherited his seat, and after the passing of Saul ha-Nasi, he was succeeded by his firstborn son Josiah ha-Nasi. Saul ha-Nasi had two sons: the first, Josiah ha-Nasi, was adulated with many honorifics, including “Light of the Exile and Crown of the Torah” (see <i>Eshkol ha-Kofer</i>, Alphabet 258); and the second was Hezekiah ha-Nasi, who was described with the honorific “the Key to Understanding” (see<i> Ḥilluq ha-Qaraʾim ve-ha-Rabbanim</i> by R. Elijah b. Abraham ha-Mizraḥi, who lived in the twelfth century, which was published by the scholar Simḥa Pinsker in <i>Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i>, appendices, p. 106). Now, they were all wise, as attested by the titles bestowed upon them by later sages, and they doubtlessly authored many works. However, to our great misfortune, none of their works have survived. Perhaps the reason for this is the same as the one that we have mentioned in our essay on R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, namely, that their opponents wiped them off the face of the Earth.<footnote id="101">See above, ¶1.25.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.03</margin>R. Salmon b. Yeruḥim (regarding whom we will write a separate essay), in the introduction to his commentary on the Decalogue, preserves Saul ha-Nasi's opinion on the Sixth Commandment,<footnote id="102">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya's listing of the prohibition on adultery as the Sixth Commandment might cause some confusion, because most Jews today deem the Sixth Commandment to be the prohibition against murder and the Seventh to be the prohibition against adultery. Ḥakham Ṭoviyya's enumeration is consistent with the Jewish tradition of Philo and Josephus (c. first century CE) and the Augustinian, Roman Catholic, and Lutheran traditions. In contrast, the Rabbinic, Greek Orthodox, and Protestant traditions count the prohibition against adultery as the Seventh Commandment. (See Moshe Weinfeld, <i>Deuteronomy 1–11: A New Translation with Introduction and Commentary</i> (The Anchor Bible) [New York: Doubleday, 1991], pp. 243f.)</footnote> <i>thou shalt not commit adultery</i> (Exodus 20:14), which he explained, disagreeing with other sages, as a general prohibition regarding all types of adultery—whether with a married or unmarried woman. (For example, R. Mevorakh b. Nathan b. Nisan ha-Levi, in his <i>Ḥatanu</i> poem<footnote id="103">The term “<i>Ḥaṭanu</i>” refers to a genre of penitential poems. In the Karaite Yom Kippur service, the refrain of these poems is: “We have sinned (<i>ḥatanu</i>) with our forefathers; we have acted perversely and wickedly.” Amongst Rabbanites, the common refrain for this genre is: “We have sinned (<i>ḥatanu</i>), our Rock; forgive us, our Creator.” See Ezra Fleischer, <i>Hebrew Liturgical Poetry in the Middle Ages</i> (Hebrew; Jerusalem: Keter Yerushalayim, 1975), pp. 203f.</footnote> for the services of Yom Kippur night—which begins “How can we lift up our heads before God, and why are we not lying down in shame and covering ourselves in disgrace?”—explains it as being a limited injunction, applying only to a married woman.)</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.04</margin>As for Josiah ha-Nasi, only fragments of writings in his name have come down to us; they are mentioned in the works of our sages, of blessed memory,<footnote id="104">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya uses the acronym <i>Ḥazal</i>; see above in ¶1.15, footnote 6. Here, the reference is clearly to the Karaite sages.</footnote> who came after him. For instance, on the issue of acquiring a wife, R. Josiah ha-Nasi writes that a wife can be acquired in six ways: <i>mohar</i>,<footnote id="105">That is, a bridal payment for a virgin, often referred to as a “bride price.” On the connection between the biblical <i>mohar</i> and the Rabbinic <i>ketuba</i>, see Deborah Greniman, “The Origins of the Ketubah: Deferred Payment or Cash up Front?” <i>Nashim</i> 4 (2001): 84–118, and for the <i>mohar</i> in the Middle Ages, see Mordechai Akiva Friedman, “The Minimum <i>Mohar</i> Payment as Reflected in the Geniza Documents: Marriage Gift or Endowment Pledge?” <i>PAAJR</i> 43 (1976): 15–47, and idem, <i>Jewish Polygyny in the Middle Ages</i> (Mosad Bialik, 1986), passim.</footnote> witnesses, writing [a contract], consent,<footnote id="106">The Hebrew word that we have translated as “consent” is <i>biʾa</i>, from the root <i>b-w-ʾ</i>. Biblical Hebrew uses this to mean sexual intercourse, and Rabbanites followed suit. Karaites, however, use the word to refer to entering into a contract with consent. Cf. Aaron ben Elijah of Nicomedia, <i>Gan ʿEden</i>, Seder Nashim, ch. 6. The Arabic translation of <i>Rosh Pinna</i> renders this as “acceptance” (<i>al-qabūl</i>). We note that the famed Karaite sage Judah Hadassi interpreted <i>biʾa</i> to mean intercourse (see <i>Eshkol ha-Kofer,</i> Alphabet 3, Letter <i>Ṭet</i>), and we have translated the following sentence accordingly.</footnote> betrothal, and acquisition (= oath).<footnote id="107">In this paragraph, the parenthetical remarks with an equal sign appear in the original Hebrew text by Ḥakham Ṭoviyya and are not editorial interventions.</footnote> Similarly, R. Judah Hadassi, author of <i>Eshkol ha-Kofer</i>, mentions six methods: <i>mohar</i>, betrothal, writing [a contract], witnesses, covenant (= oath), and intercourse.<footnote id="108">We have translated this according to Judah Hadassi's view that<i> biʾa</i> referred to intercourse, as described immediately above in footnote 104. We note, though, that the Arabic text here renders <i>biʾa</i> as <i>al-qabūl</i>, suggesting that Ḥakham Ṭoviyya (or perhaps his Arabic translators) believed that it should be understood as “consent.”</footnote> However, R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi limits them to five, namely, betrothal, taking (= marriage), <i>mohar</i>, covenant (= oath), and witnesses. (See R. Aaron of Nicomedia, <i>Gan ʿEden</i>, Seder Nashim, Chapter 6.)</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.05</margin>It is widely known that Karaites today, instead of having these six or five conditions, write only three, in brief, in the marriage document: (1) <i>mohar</i>, (2) writing, and (3) consent. </p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.06</margin>From what has been said thus far, it is apparent that the activities of Saul ha-Nasi and his son Josiah ha-Nasi were not particularly prominent in the Exile.<footnote id="109">This is not to imply that the opinions of these sages were famous among the Jews of the Land of Israel but simply that most Jews of the time lived in the Diaspora, so if these sages' opinions were not famous among the Jews of the Diaspora, they were not famous among the Jews at all.</footnote> On the other hand, Josiah's disciple, the sage Benjamin al-Nahawandi, whom we will discuss here, was widely acknowledged for his role in the development of the Karaite faith.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.07</margin>The sage Benjamin b. Moses al-Nahawandi (may his soul rest in Eden) was born in the city of Nahawand, as attested by the epithet “Nahawandi.” It is a city in Media, to which the Ten Tribes were exiled after the fall of the Kingdom of Israel. According to the testimony of the sage R. Jacob b. Isaac al-Qirqisani (who is known among scholars as “Abu Yusuf Yaʿqub”), he lived 30 or 40 years after R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, in the days of Caliph al-Muʿṭasim Billah (r. 834–842); he was a disciple of Josiah ha-Nasi, as we have mentioned above; and he himself had many disciples, among them the famed sage Daniel al-Qumisi.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.08</margin>It appears that Benjamin al-Nahawandi occupied the position of judge<footnote id="110">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya uses two Hebrew words for “judge” here, <i>shofeṭ</i> and <i>dayyan</i>. If the two are not synonymous, the distinction is not obvious.</footnote> in his hometown of Nahawand. While he occupied the bench of justice, he composed the <i>Book of Laws</i>, which we will discuss below, for day-to-day usage. He followed R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi very closely in his explication of the Torah's commandments; as the expression goes: “He ate of his bread and drank of his cup.”<footnote id="111">Cf. II Samuel 12:3.</footnote> However, he did not follow ʿAnan blindly. He was instrumental in establishing the foundations of the Karaite faith, to the extent that many Arab scholars considered him, too, to be one of the founders of Karaism; in fact, they referred to the group as <i>Aṣḥāb ʿAnān wa-Binyāmīn</i>, literally, “those who follow ʿAnan and Benjamin.” Some of our Rabbanite brethren likewise consider Benjamin al-Nahawandi to be one of the three founders of the Karaite faith: (1) ʿAnan ha-Nasi, (2) his son Saul ha-Nasi, and (3) Benjamin al-Nahawandi.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.09</margin>R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi took freedom of opinion to the extreme. He would say that [when one endeavors] to understand the Torah's commandments, a disciple has the right to oppose the opinion of his teacher, and a son can contradict his father, and the father may not say: “Why are you contesting my word?” Also, a younger brother may oppose the older, as long as he can buttress his position from the words of Scripture. And in this, he followed the axiom established by our early sages, of blessed memory, who were wont to say: “Whenever there is a desecration of the name of God, one does not accord honor even to a master.”<footnote id="112">In fact, this quote is not from early Karaite sages but from the Babylonian Talmud,<i> Berakhot</i> 19b.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.10</margin>It was during the lifetime of R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi that the followers of ʿAnan ha-Nasi began to call themselves “Scripturalists” or “Karaites” and no longer “ʿAnanites.”</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.11</margin>R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi wrote most of his works in Hebrew, unlike R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, who wrote all of his works in Aramaic, as we mentioned in the essay devoted to him,<footnote id="113">See above, ¶1.24.</footnote> and also unlike most subsequent sages, who wrote most of their works in Arabic and not Hebrew. I am referring specifically to the Karaite sages who lived in Egypt, the Land of Israel, Aram (Syria),<footnote id="114">Parentheses in the original text.</footnote> Babylonia, and the East in general, where the Arabic language was widely spoken by the people. This [state of affairs] lasted until the end of the fifteenth century, after which almost all Karaite sages, in all lands, wrote their works exclusively in Hebrew.<footnote id="115">According to Marina Rustow, after ʿAnan, the Karaites generally abandoned Aramaic, “which was too burdened with the Talmudic past and now became the sole province of the Rabbanite camp. Instead, they turned their attention to Hebrew, the language of the Bible, and to Arabic, the new lingua franca of scholarly endeavor. The result of this shift was an outpouring of grammatical and exegetical work occasioned by the renaissance of Hebrew study and a stream of Arabic Bible translations and commentaries that would profoundly affect the history of Medieval Jewish Biblical exegesis” (<i>Scripture and Schism</i>, p. 63).</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.12</margin>Of all the literary output of Benjamin al-Nahawandi, very little has come down to us in full. Among [this] is his <i>Book of Laws</i>, which was published by the Karaite Society of Supporters of the Press in the year 5594 (1834 CE) in the city of Gozlova,<footnote id="116">Today known as “Eupatoria” or “Yevpatoria.”</footnote> Russia, together with <i>Mivḥar Yesharim</i> by R. Aaron I and <i>Sefer ha-ʿOsher</i> by R. Jacob b. Reuben (may their souls rest in Eden), both commentaries on the Prophets and Writings. This publication can be found here in the library of our Religious Court.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.13</margin>The <i>Book of Laws</i> is known among the more recent sages under the name <i>Masʾat Binyamin</i>. It includes laws about monetary matters, laws about capital crimes, and more. They are all recorded there in no specific order, with the various topics interspersed, as is the case with [the writings of] most early sages. At the beginning of his <i>Book of Laws</i>, he writes at length about the obligations of judges and witnesses, and for every rule, he brings a verse from Scripture for support. It is worth noting that he concludes the book by saying that there is no problem if Karaites use rulings that are not mentioned in the book but rather are practiced by Rabbanites, as long as there is no disagreement between them and us [about the given issue].</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.14</margin>We shall comment here on some of the laws in this book, some of which differ from the opinions of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi and later Karaite sages:</p>

<quotation>1. <margin side="right">¶2.15</margin>He prohibits a man from marrying a woman with whom he shared the same wet nurse [in infancy]. There is no hint of this in the Torah. Although he relies on a verse in Song of Songs, in which two infants who suckle from the same breast are considered siblings—<i>Oh that thou wert as my brother, that sucked the breasts of my mother!</i> (Song of Songs 8:1)—it is very flimsy.<footnote id="117">Literally, “a bruised reed” (II Kings 18:21).</footnote> In this [ruling], R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi inclines toward the opinion of our Muslim brethren.

2. <margin side="right">¶2.16</margin>In the verse <i>If brethren dwell together, and one of them die, and have no child, the wife of the dead shall not be married abroad unto one not of his kin</i> (Deuteronomy 25:5), he explains the word <i>brethren</i> here as referring to actual [biological] brothers, so he obligates a man to marry his dead brother's fiancée. (This is also the opinion of the Samaritan sect.) On the other hand, R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, and other sages who came after him, maintain that it refers to a kinsman. In this, his (= Benjamin's) view is close to that of our Rabbanite brethren; however, the Rabbanites understand the words <i>wife of the dead</i> as referring not to the dead man's fiancée but to his actual wife.

3. <margin side="right">¶2.17</margin>According to the opinion of R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi, a husband inherits from his wife, which is against the opinion of Karaite sages. Here, as well, his view tends toward that of our Rabbanite brethren.<footnote id="118">According to the Mishna, <i>Ketubbot</i> 6:1, a husband inherits from his wife upon her death. This is the Rabbanite ruling even when the woman has surviving children. Inasmuch as we can tell from Ḥakham Ṭoviyya's words, it seems that Nahawandi, too, would apply this rule across the board; however, it is possible that he would have restricted it to cases where the woman does not have children to inherit from her.</footnote>

4. <margin side="right">¶2.18</margin>R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi was among the proponents of <i>rikkuv</i>,<footnote id="119">This word means “grafting” and refers to an approach taken by a number of early Karaite sages regarding the laws of incest and consanguineous marriage. The approach takes a wide definition of forbidden relationships, for it grafts all the relatives of the husband onto the wife, and vice versa—that is, it views the two parties as forming a single family, which is twice as large as either of the individual families, and thus the pool of people that are forbidden sexual partners is twice as large. See above in ¶1.24, footnote 27, for a discussion of this matter.</footnote> who forbid all the wife's relatives to all the husband's relatives because they consider husband and wife to be like one body, relying on the verse: <i>Therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother and shall cleave unto his wife, and they shall be one flesh</i> (Genesis 2:24). (See <i>Masʾat Binyamin</i>, top of p. 5.)

5. <margin side="right">¶2.19</margin>R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi grants decisive value to oral testimony [of the accused], declaring a verbal confession of more value than 1,000 reliable witnesses.

6. <margin side="right">¶2.20</margin>According to the opinion of R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi, it is incumbent upon a man<footnote id="120">The word used here is <i>ish</i>, which can mean either “man” or “person.” Presumably, Nahawandi would view this rule as also incumbent on women, but we cannot prove this from the language.</footnote> to bring a foundling<footnote id="121">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya here uses the Talmudic term <i>asufi,</i> literally, “a gathered one.” See Mishna, <i>Qiddushin</i> 4:1.</footnote> into his home, sustain him, and educate him. He writes in his <i>Book of Laws:</i> “[In the case of] an abandoned child, one is required to sustain him and to teach him Torah, as it is written: <i>[B]ut thou wast cast out in the open field […] I said unto thee: In thy blood, live</i> (Ezekiel 16:5–6).<footnote id="122">This exegesis derives a law not from the legal or even non-legal sections of the Pentateuch but from an allegorical prophecy in Ezekiel, where God speaks of the Israelite people as an abandoned little girl and says that He has adopted her. Although this passage does not give any explicit ruling for interpersonal conduct, Nahawandi derives from it that adults must adopt abandoned children.</footnote>

7. <margin side="right">¶2.21</margin>Regarding the commandment of inheritance, he writes: One who leaves his father's dominion to lead an impious life in his father's lifetime does not inherit his father's wealth, because he has already left his father's dominion. [This is] like the sons of Moses, who were not with Moses, so his prophecy was inherited instead by his disciple and attendant, Joshua bin Nun. But if the father gives him a share together with his [other] sons, [then in this case that son does receive a portion of the inheritance, because] he (= the father) has dominion over himself and his riches [to bequeath them to whomever he wants].<footnote id="123">Here, too, Nahawandi is deriving a halakhic rule from a non-legal part of Scripture, though this time it is a narrative portion in the Pentateuch and therefore a more obvious source of halakha than an allegorical vision in a prophetic book.</footnote>

8. <margin side="right">¶2.22</margin>R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi says that a father is obligated to teach his son Torah upon weaning and defines this age as three years old, relying on verses in Scripture (I Samuel 1:24 and II Chronicles 31:16).</quotation>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.23</margin>In his <i>Book of Laws</i>, R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi makes mention of another book of his, <i>The Book of Commandments</i>, in which he evidently explained all the commandments of the Torah; however, this book has been lost from us, alas for what has been lost!<footnote id="124">This expression is taken from the Babylonian Talmud, <i>Sanhedrin</i> 11a.</footnote> Only a few statements, from a handful of passages, have survived from it, in [quotations in] books of later Karaite sages.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.24</margin>The scholar Abraham Harkavy gathered all those various fragments and published them together with the remnants of the<i> Book of Commandments</i> by R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> (see his book <i>Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i>, Part II, pp. 175–184, which he published in St. Petersburg, Russia in 1903; see also my essay “The Writings of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>”).<footnote id="125">That is, the essay printed as the first part of <i>Rosh Pinna</i>.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.25</margin>We will now quote some of his ideas contained in the aforementioned statements, in addition to the aforecited:</p>

<quotation>1. <margin side="right">¶2.26</margin>He says that a ritually clean flying <i>shereẓ</i> (crawling creature) can be recognized by means of three signs: i) wings with which it flies; ii) four legs on which it walks; and iii) two hind legs with which it hops. He is referring to the four types of locusts that are permitted for consumption by the Torah, namely, <i>arbé,</i> <i>solʿam</i>, <i>ḥargol</i>, and <i>ḥagav</i> (see Leviticus 11:22).<footnote id="126">We have left these species names untranslated because their identifications are uncertain. Nonetheless, at least according to Nahawandi, our inability to identify the specific species would not present a halakhic impediment to eating them, as long as we can identify the physical signs that make them kosher. For practices among world Jewry, see Zohar Amar, “The Eating of Locusts in Jewish Tradition after the Talmudic Period,” <i>Torah u-Madda Journal</i> 11 (2002–2003), pp. 186–202, especially p. 197, with reference to Karaites in the Middle Ages.</footnote>

2. <margin side="right">¶2.27</margin>He says that one must perform circumcision with flint knives; in other words, with a razor made from flint. If flint knives are unobtainable, one may circumcise with anything at hand. This opinion contradicts that of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, who writes that circumcision is [performed exclusively] with scissors.

3. <margin side="right">¶2.28</margin>He also says that wherever no males are present, a woman may perform the circumcision, as it is written: <i>[Then Zipporah took a flint,] and cut off the foreskin of her son</i> (Exodus 4:25). This opinion likewise differs from that of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>, who ruled that the circumciser must be a male. It should be noted, however, that al-Nahawandi later clarifies that a female is allowed to circumcise only her own sons, for it says about Zipporah: <i>and cut off the foreskin of her son</i>, as we have cited above.<footnote id="127">On female circumcisers in the Middle Ages, see Elisheva Baumgarten, <i>Mothers and Children: Jewish Family Life in Medieval Europe</i> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2004), p. 65, with literature in the notes.</footnote></quotation>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.29</margin>R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi opined that there is an angel who mediates between God and His creations; in other words, God created one angel, and that angel created the world and all it contains. (See<i> Eshkol ha-Kofer</i>, Alphabet 98.) [Nahawandi posited] all this in order to distance [God] from corporeality, because, according to him, God is entirely, purely spiritual, and He would be essentially imperfect if He were in contact with anything physical. Scholars compare this opinion to that of the sage Philo Judaeus, who is known as “Philo of Alexandria” (born in Alexandria 20 years before the birth of Jesus of Nazareth and died there circa 50 CE), who gleaned most of his wisdom from the books of the Greek philosophers and who likewise placed an intermediary between God and the world. He calls this mediator <i>logos</i>, literally, “the word.” We find something similar to this in the Gospel of John, where it is written, “In the beginning was the `word,' and the word was with God etc.”<footnote id="128">John 1:1, King James translation with added quotation marks to reflect Babovich's Hebrew.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.30</margin>And in order to strengthen this unusual opinion of his, R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi brought proofs from many different verses in the Torah where we encounter angels. For instance: <i>Now I know that the Lord is greater than all gods; yea, for that they dealt proudly against them</i> (Exodus 18:11)<i>.</i> Here, R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi mistakenly interprets the word <i>gods</i> as referring to an angel, when, in fact, it refers to false gods, such as the sun, the moon, and the stars, which many of the ancients considered deities. Additionally, many of them believed that all natural forces, such as storms, lightning, rain, or powerful animals, such as the ox or the elephant, were gods. And in this particular passage, Jethro, the father-in-law of Moses, who used to believe in these false gods, now acknowledges that the God of Israel, who is called <i>the Lord</i>, who took them out of Egypt, is the strongest and most powerful of them all.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.31</margin>We should add here that it is entirely possible that R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi's extreme distancing of corporeality from God was due to the influence of Arab sages, as some scholars suppose.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.32</margin>It should be known that Arab theologians were divided into two schools. The first school was that of the <i>Mutakallimīn</i> (Kalamists), which, according to scholars [of history], began in the eighth century. They were also called “the Ashʿarites,” after the Arab sage Ashʿari (873–937), who strengthened the foundations of this sect. The second sect was called the<i> Muʿtazilīn</i> (Mutazilites). The most well-known sage among the <i>Mutakallimīn</i> was the philosopher Ibn Sina (987–1037), whom the Europeans call “Avicenna”; the most well-known sage among the <i>Muʿtazilīn</i> was the philosopher Ibn Rushd (1126–1198), whom the Europeans call “Averroes.”</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.33</margin><i>Mutakallimīn</i> is an Arabic word, which translates to “those who discuss.” Scholars explain that the word refers to “the ones who use logic to prove their opinions.” <i>Muʿtazilīn</i>, too, is an Arabic word, which translates to “those who are separated”; that is, “separated from the school of the <i>Mutakallimīn,</i>” for the <i>Muʿtazilīn</i> differed from the <i>Mutakallamīn</i> on some important points in their respective philosophies.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.34</margin>For instance, the <i>Mutakallamīn</i> rejected the concept of free will and free choice; they said that whenever a person does anything, they do so not out of their own desire but according to divine decree. By contrast, the <i>Muʿtazilīn</i> believed that man acts out of free will and endeavored to support their beliefs with proofs. Their greatest proof was that they would ask: how can man be held accountable for his actions, if they are not performed by his choice or will? How can man receive reward or punishment for something he has done, if this deed was caused, necessarily, by God?</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.35</margin>However, both of these schools concur that the universe was created out of naught; that is, out of nothing (<i>ex nihilo</i>).<footnote id="129">Although Ḥakham Ṭoviyya prints the Latin expression as <i>ex-nihil</i>, Latin grammar requires that <i>nihil</i> be in the ablative case following <i>ex</i>: <i>nihilo</i>.</footnote> In this, the two align with our holy Torah and gainsay the opinion of the Greek philosophers, headed by the famous Aristotle, who maintained that it is not possible even for God (heaven forbid) to create something out of nothing and that in the beginning there was primordial matter called “hyle”<footnote id="130">Greek ὕλη; Ḥakham Ṭoviyya uses the Hebrew form <i>hiyyuli</i>, which has been standard in Hebrew since the Middle Ages.</footnote> from which God created the universe. They also are against the opinion of the Greek philosopher Democritus, who said that in the beginning there were atoms and God created the universe out of these atoms.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.36</margin>The Mutazilites expended much energy in interpreting the words of the Holy<footnote id="131">See above in ¶1.36, footnote 59.</footnote> Qurʾan in a way that would distance all corporeal descriptions and corporeal actions from God. R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi saw some of them (= their words) and followed their path, and out of this principle emerged his idea that God created an angel and that angel created the universe—all, as we have written above, in order that God not come in contact with any corporeal thing, such as this world.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.37</margin>Should one desire to enter into this great thicket of scholarship to acquire more knowledge about the two aforementioned schools, “the speakers” and “the separate ones,” and also about creation <i>ex nihilo,</i> one should consult the philosophical books on these matters. Such works by Karaites include those of R. Joseph b. Abraham al-Baṣir or the Seer (eleventh century), who wrote them in Arabic, namely: <i>Kitāb al-Muḥtawī</i>, which has been translated into Hebrew as <i>Sefer ha-Neʿimot</i>; and <i>Kitāb al-Tamyīz</i>, known alternatively as <i>Kitāb al-Manṣūrī</i>, which was translated into Hebrew as <i>Maḥkimat Peti</i>. One should also consult <i>ʿEẓ Ḥayyim</i> by Aaron II of Nicomedia (fourteenth century), and quench one's thirst from these deep wellsprings. </p>

<quotation><margin side="right">¶2.37.1</margin>See the work of Russian theologian Mitrofan Muretov on this topic: “The Logos Theory of Philo of Alexandria and the Apostle John” (Moscow, 1885).<footnote id="132">In the original printing of <i>Rosh Pinna</i>, this note appears only at the end of the chapter, on p. 74, so ¶2.37 ends with the words, “See p. 74.” We have deleted these words from our Hebrew text because they are irrelevant to the layout of this edition. We also note that the original Arabic text erroneously states 1875, which we have corrected to 1885.</footnote></quotation>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶2.38</margin>We conclude our discussion of this matter by saying that the Karaite sages as a whole did not accept the opinion of R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi in regards to the creation of that first angel, even though the vast majority of them did believe in angels. This is because, according to the opinion of the Karaite sages, belief in an intermediary between the Creator and the universe stands in contradiction to the perfect faith of the religion, which maintains that there cannot be any intermediary between the Creator and the universe; that God created the world on His own, without any intermediary, through His word alone; and that God governs all people and all His creations without any intermediary, as it is written: <i>The Lord</i> <i>is good to all; and His tender mercies are over all His works</i> (Psalms 145:10)<footnote id="133">In common printings of the Tanakh, this is verse 9. Both the Hebrew and Arabic texts of <i>Rosh Pinna</i> print verse 10. We have retained this as verse 10, because the division of Psalms (including the opening of different Psalms) has not always been uniform and our author may have been familiar with a tradition in which this is verse 10.</footnote>.</p>

<p>The first to oppose R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi on this point was his disciple R. Daniel al-Qumisi, as we will explain in the essay that we will compose about him. The next to oppose him was the great luminary R. Joseph the Seer b. Abraham (of blessed memory) who is called “al-Baṣir”; he writes in his book <i>Maḥkimat Peti</i>: “We will explain here the utter lack of any intermediaries (that is, between God and the world) with evidence to disprove the words of the Rabbanite <i>Shiʿur Qoma</i>,<footnote id="134">There are various texts and recensions of <i>Shiʿur Qoma</i>. For an academic collection of such texts, see Martin Samuel Cohen (ed.), <i>The Shiʿur Qomah: Texts and Recensions</i> (Tübingen: J.C.B. Mohr [Paul Siebeck], 1985).</footnote> of others who speak of two divine forces, and of Benjamin al-Nahawandi, who says that God created an angel and that angel created the world, etc.” (see Simḥa Pinsker, <i>Liqquṭé</i> Qadmoniyyot, p. 199). Similarly, all the Karaite sages who came after R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi did not accept his idea of an intermediary between God and the world. Nonetheless, the power<footnote id="135">Hebrew <i>koaḥ</i>, meaning “prestige,” “authority,” “popularity.”</footnote> of this teacher of ours was great among the Karaites with respect to his explication of the Torah's commandments<i>,</i> although this too was only until the appearance of other sages, who delved deeply into the commandments and were more nuanced in interpreting them.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.39</margin>In the Yom Kippur prayer book, there is a <i>seliḥa</i> (penitential prayer) attributed to Benjamin al-Nahawandi. It begins: “The beloved daughter of God arises at dawn, / Will the red of her stain become clean like white? / She praises Thee with a song: <i>For the Leader; upon Aijeleth ha-Shahar”</i><footnote id="136">The last line of the stanza is a quote from Psalms 22:1.</footnote> (see<i> Siddur for Yom ha-Kippurim</i>, published by Jacob Szyszman, p. 312). Perhaps he wrote other compositions of this sort,<footnote id="137">Hebrew <i>miqẓoaʿ</i>, which Babovich usually uses in the sense of a scholarly field or endeavor but can perhaps also mean “genre.”</footnote> but [if so], they have unfortunately not survived.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.40</margin>R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi writes that there are three <i>beqarim</i>,<footnote id="138">Literally “mornings”; that is, times of day referred to by the Hebrew word <i>boqer</i>.</footnote> namely, 1) the beginning of the visible glow, which is called <i>shaḥar</i>; 2) dawn, before sunrise; and 3) sunrise. Our sages also divide evening into three <i>ʿaravim</i>,<footnote id="139">Literally “evenings”; that is, times of day referred to by the Hebrew word <i>ʿerev</i>.</footnote> namely, 1) sunset; 2) the setting of its glow, and 3) nightfall (see <i>Sefer ha-Adderet</i>, Sanctification of the Months, Chapter 2). However, R. Isaac, author of <i>Or ha-Levana</i>,<footnote id="140">Ḥakham Isaac b. Solomon (1754–1824) was a Crimean-born Karaite author, an expert in calendrical matters, and a liturgical poet. Some of his poetry is included in the Karaite Siddur.</footnote> rejects this opinion and leaves only two <i>ʿaravim</i>, namely, 1) the beginning of the sun's dip beyond the horizon and 2) the completion of the sun's setting beyond the horizon (examine his <i>Or ha-Levana</i> carefully).</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.41</margin>R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi concedes that the establishment of the New Moon must be done according to the sighting of the moon. However, he writes that in antiquity,<footnote id="141">Because the one piece of evidence brought here is from the pericope of Noah in the book of Genesis, it would seem that “antiquity” refers to the period before the giving of the Torah. However, from Nahawandi's actual words, as preserved by Yeshuʿa b. Judah, it seems that this form of calendar survived throughout the biblical period as a civil calendar, whereas the calendar based on sighting the moon was used as a religious calendar, “for the commandments and the festivals.” See Zahava Yod, <i>The Remnant and the Relic: From the Books of Commandments of the Early Karaites</i> (Daly City: The Karaite Press, 2017), p. 13.</footnote> the months were fixed according to the solar month—they considered each month to be 30 days. He brings proof from the Torah for this opinion, based on what it says (Genesis 7:11; 8:3–4): <i>In the six hundredth year of Noah's life, in the second month, on the seventeenth day of the month, on the same day were all the fountains of the great deep broken up, and the windows of heaven were opened. … And the waters returned from off the Earth continually; and after the end of 150 days, the waters decreased. And the ark rested in the seventh month, on the seventeenth day of the month, upon the mountains of Ararat.</i> He says that after every five years, they would make the sixth year a leap year of 13 months, the thirteenth month comprising the missing five days from each of the past six solar years.<footnote id="142">That is, each year would consists of 360 days (12×30), five days less than the solar year of 365; thus, at the end of six years, these days would amount to a full month of 30 days.</footnote> After the passage of 72 years, everything would return to its strength;<footnote id="143">Cf. Exodus 14:27.</footnote> that is, the cycle restarts.<footnote id="144">It is unclear what the point of this 72-year cycle is. Ostensibly, the idea would be that each leap year would make the calendar drift by one month, so only after 12 leap years would the calendar return to its original position. However, the number of extra days in the leap year (30) is identical to the number of days lost over the six-year period, so there should not be any calendar drift.</footnote> He refers to solar months as “seasonal months.” (This system of calculation is quite similar to that of our brethren the Copts, currently living here in Egypt. The only difference is that our brethren the Copts count an additional five or six days at the end of each year, which they call <i>ayyām al-nasī [al- qubṭiyya]</i>, whereas the ancient calculation aggregates all of these days into an extra month at the end of every six years, making that year a leap year of 13 months.)</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.42</margin>R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi wrote commentaries on most of the books of Scripture, which are mentioned in the books of later sages. The well-known Rabbanite sage Abraham ibn Ezra (may his soul rest in Eden) says that Benjamin al-Nahawandi belongs to a class of outstanding exegetes. The [later] sages mention his commentaries on Genesis, Judges, Isaiah, Daniel, Song of Songs, and Ecclesiastes. Most of these commentaries are now lost, with only a very few extant. Among these is his [complete] commentary on Ecclesiastes, which he composed in Arabic to ensure that common people would be able to understand, because this book is entirely ethical exhortation for the masses, whose common language in those days was Arabic. The manuscript of this book is at the Imperial Library in St. Petersburg, Russia, having been brought there by the scholar Abraham Firkovich (may his soul rest in Eden). (See<i> Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i> by the late scholar R. Simḥa Pinsker, the great researcher of Karaite literature<i>,</i> in the appendices, p. 109.)</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.43</margin>In his commentary on the book of Isaiah, [on the section] beginning with the verse <i>Behold, My servant shall prosper, he shall be exalted and lifted up, and shall be very high</i> (chapter 52:13, [through] the entire chapter 53), he explains that this refers to the “messianic era,” the golden age when <i>nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more</i> (Isaiah 2:4). This is in contrast to most other exegetes,<footnote id="145">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya is referring to Jewish exegetes. Famously, Christian exegetes understand the whole passage as referring to Jesus, which forced nearly all Jewish exegetes to respond with some other past or future reference that could plausibly fit.</footnote> who relate it to the past, to [the reign of] King Hezekiah.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.44</margin>Some claim that R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi traveled to Jerusalem toward the end of his life and passed away there. As proof for their theory, they cite what he wrote at the end of his <i>Masʾat Binyamin</i>: “Abundant peace to all those living in the Exile, from me, Benjamin b. Moses”—as if it were only possible to address those living in the Exile from the Land of Israel. Our opinion is that we cannot draw any conclusions from this, either positive or negative.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.45</margin>Nevertheless, after all the foregoing, we must concede that our research leads us to state that R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi definitely lived in Jerusalem for at least a short period, and that for several reasons. The first reason is, as we have stated above, that he was a disciple of R. Josiah ha-Nasi, who was located in Jerusalem. The second reason is that the epithet “al-Nahawandi” might be evidence, because everyone knows that people do not call an individual after the name of their hometown or country until after they leave; it is the people of the new place of residence who call them after the name of their hometown or country.<footnote id="146">Modern scholarship does not accept the claim that Nahawandi, or, for that matter, Josiah ha-Nasi, was ever in Jerusalem, but rather maintains that Karaite settlement in Jerusalem began only after the time of Nahawandi. See above in ¶1.21, footnote 16.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶2.46</margin>In the order of memorial prayers [recited] on the Sabbath, the name of R. Ḥakham Benjamin al-Nahawandi is mentioned immediately after that of Saul ha-Nasi; may their memories be blessed, may their light shine over us, and may their merit protect us, Amen.</p>

<center><i>Ḥakham Ṭoviyya b. Simḥa (of blessed memory) Levi-Babovich</i></center>

<h1>III An Article on R. Daniel al-Qumisi Ninth Century CE)</h1>

<p>By: Ḥakham Ṭoviyya b. Simḥa Levi-Babovich</p>

<p>Cairo, Egypt</p>

<p>1947</p>

<h1><margin side="right">¶3.01</margin>III R. Daniel b. Moses al-Qumisi or Damaghani (Ninth Century CE)</h1> 

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.02</margin>R. Daniel b. Moses is usually referred to as “al-Qumisi,” although occasionally “Damaghani.” These epithets attest that he was from Persia, since Damaghan is the main city in the province of Qumis, which is in the region of Tabaristan in Persia; however, it seems that when he was still a young man, he traveled to Jerusalem and settled there until the end of his life, and he always strove to increase the number of Karaites in the Holy Land.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.03</margin>In this context, one should know that in the ninth century, a circular was distributed calling for travel to Jerusalem in order to establish a spiritual center there. Subsequently, it was discovered that the author of this circular was Daniel al-Qumisi. In it, he calls for Karaites around the world to convene in Jerusalem, saying that the Muslim leaders grant the Karaites freedom in all aspects of their lives and religion and that they have no need to fear the Rabbanites. He also dispenses advice on how to establish a settlement in Jerusalem. He proposes that every [Karaite] community in other countries send at least five people<footnote id="147">Hebrew <i>anashim</i>, which could mean “men” specifically.</footnote> there at its own expense, where they will sustain themselves from the funds of the community that sent them. These people will live lives of piety in Jerusalem, fulfilling all the commandments in accordance with the rules, and they will take upon themselves the custom of the Mourners of Zion,<footnote id="148">For the identity of this group, see above, ¶1.21.</footnote> with weeping and mourning for the destruction of the Temple, eating no meat and drinking no wine. Then God will find favor in them and renew their days as of old.<footnote id="149">Cf. Lamentations 5:21.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.04</margin>This call was directed against some of the Karaites in Babylonia, who used to say that one should not travel to Jerusalem until the arrival of the Messiah; God had dispersed the people of Israel from there because of their sins, and He would gather them there with the arrival of the Messiah. Daniel al-Qumisi, however, said that one should not wait for the arrival of the Messiah but travel there before his arrival to beg God's forgiveness for our sins, in order that He hasten and expedite the Messiah's arrival. This is what Daniel al-Qumisi said:</p>

<quotation>When one person is furious with another, is it not the universal practice that the offending party<footnote id="150">Hebrew <i>niqẓaf</i>, which literally refers to the one against whom the fury is directed.</footnote> approaches the enraged to appease him? [Does not] the offending child come to the father's door, and a servant to the master's? And if the king is furious with one of his ministers and imprisons him, is it not incumbent upon him to mourn, change his clothes, and abstain from ministerial pleasures, until the king hears of it and is appeased, restoring him to his station?… All the more so, if the Creator of the universe is furious with a creature—is it proper for him to eat and drink before he has returned to Him?… Know that the degenerates of Israel say to one another, “We should not go to Jerusalem until He gathers us, just as He cast us out.” This is what the infuriating and foolish ones utter! For even if God had not given us a commandment to go to Jerusalem from the [other] lands wailing bitterly,<footnote id="151">Cf. Jeremiah 6:26.</footnote> we nonetheless would know by our own lights that offending parties must come to the door of the incensed to appease him, as I have written above. All the more so [in our case], for God commanded the exiled to come to Jerusalem and present themselves at all times there in mourning, fasting, weeping, and sorrowful, in sackcloth and bitterness, day and night, etc.</quotation>

<p indent="no">(See <i>Textes<footnote id="152">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya's misspelling of English “texts” is presumably due to his greater familiarity with French.</footnote> and Studies</i> by Dr. Jacob Mann,<footnote id="153">Jacob Mann (1888–1940) was one of the foremost scholars of Near Eastern Jewish history. Born in Przemyśl, Galicia (today in southern Poland) to Ḥasidic parents, he eventually went to study in London, where he pursued both Rabbinic ordination at the prestigious Jews College and a secular education. His first book, entitled <i>The Jews in Egypt and Palestine Under the Fatimid Caliphs</i>, was published in 1920 and considered a masterpiece by scholars. His second major work, <i>Texts and Studies in Jewish History and Literature</i>, was published in 1941 and dealt extensively with the history of the Karaites of the Near East and Europe as reflected in the documents of the Cairo Geniza. He also served as a professor of Jewish History, Hebrew Literature, and Talmud at Hebrew Union College in Cincinnati, Ohio until his passing in 1940.</footnote> vol. II, Philadelphia, 1935, p. 5, note 8.<footnote id="154">Mann's monumental book was translated into Arabic and published in serialized form in the Egyptian Karaite periodical <i>Al-Kalim</i> (late 1940s-early 1950s) by Farag Musa al-Sergani (1890–1949). Farag al-Sergani was a noted principal of the local Karaite school for a decade. See Yosef Algamil, <i>Karaite Jewry</i>, English section, p. 82.</footnote>)</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.05</margin>We should note at this point that the Karaites had already been established in Jerusalem in the days of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi (as we have already mentioned in our essay on ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>);<footnote id="155">See above in ¶1.21, footnote 16, where we note that modern scholars do not accept this claim, believing instead that the Karaite settlement in Jerusalem did not begin in earnest until the second half of the ninth century, during Qumisi's lifetime.</footnote> R. Daniel al-Qumisi only made an effort to increase their number, and [until this point], the Karaites had settled not only in Jerusalem but also in other places in the Land of Israel. R. Jacob al-Qirqisani mentions the name of a sage Malik al-Ramli, who resided in the town of Ramla at the time of R. ʿAnan Ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.06</margin>And here it is important to point out that the objective of the Karaites in traveling to Jerusalem was not at all “political,” as some newly minted<footnote id="156">Cf. Deuteronomy 32:17.</footnote> scholars would have us believe; on the contrary, it was “religious.”<footnote id="157">The quotation marks around the words “political” and “religious” are in the original Hebrew.</footnote> The scholar Jacob Mann expressed the truth<footnote id="158">Cf. Psalms 37:30 and Proverbs 8:7.</footnote> of this matter, when he said:</p>

<quotation>... Therefore, when ʿAnan arose circa 760, he did not indulge in messianic delusions and concentrated solely on establishing a new religious sect based on the Written Torah, in opposition to Rabbanite tradition. Therefore, he was successful in warding off any suspicion on the part of the government and in ensuring that his movement would be more viable than the sects that had preceded him.</quotation>

<p indent="no">(See his article, “The Messianic Movements in the Days of the First Crusades,” published in the monthly <i>Ha-Tequfa</i>, vol. 23.)<footnote id="159">This journal is now available online: <url>https://archive.org/details/hatekufah23telauoft</url>. The passage that Ḥakham Ṭoviyya quotes is on p. 251.</footnote></p>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.07</margin>R. Daniel al-Qumisi lived at the end of the ninth century, since R. Jacob al-Qirqisani, in his <i>Book of Lights and Watchtowers</i> (<i>Kitāb</i> <i>al-Anwār wa-al-Marāqib</i>), which was written in Arabic in 937, mentions the name of R. Daniel Damaghani at the very end in his history of the various Jewish sects (after the names of Benjamin al-Nahawandi; Moses al-Zaʿafrani, who is known as “Abu ʿAmran al-Tiflisi”; Malik al-Ramli; Ishmael al-ʿUkbari; and Mishwi al-ʿUkbari). (Ukbara is the name of a town on the southern shore of the Tigris River.)<footnote id="160">The sentence Ukbara and its location appears in a footnote in the original Arabic publication of <i>Rosh Pinna</i>. In order to harmonize the Arabic and Hebrew, we have moved the footnote into the main Arabic text of paragraph 3.7 in our edition.</footnote></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.08</margin>A Rabbanite sage by the name of R. Naṭronai<footnote id="161">R. Naṭronai bar Hilai (ninth century), a <i>gaʾon</i> of the Academy of Sura, Iraq. His responsa have been edited and published by Robert Brody (Jerusalem: Machon Ofek, 2011).</footnote>—as cited in the Siddur of R. ʿAmram<footnote id="162">This is a prayer book by R. ʿAmram b. Sheshna (ninth century), a <i>gaʾon</i> of the Academy of Sura, Iraq. This book, in various forms, has been published a number of times, including the edition by Daniel Goldschmidt (Jerusalem: Mossad Harav Kook, 1971).</footnote>—calls R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi “the father of the father of Daniel,” meaning that he (= al-Qumisi) was a grandson of ʿAnan ha-Nasi. If this is correct, then he was of the same generation as Josiah ha-Nasi, who was likewise a grandson of ʿAnan. But we cannot currently determine whether R. Naṭronai spoke the truth or considered Daniel al-Qumisi to be a spiritual descendant of ʿAnan (that is, he followed in the footsteps of ʿAnan ha-Nasi), in which case we would construe the words “father of the father” figuratively, to mean that Daniel was one of the students of the students of ʿAnan, in [their] time. This is the opinion of the scholars Zunz<footnote id="163">Leopold Zunz (1794–1886, Germany) was the founder of the academic study of Judaism, known in German as <i>Wissenschaft des Judentums</i>.</footnote> and R. Simḥa Pinsker (may his soul rest in Eden) (see <i>Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i>, p. 189, footnote 3). <b>(See also Appendix I.)</b></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.09</margin>According to the hypothesis of some sages, R. Daniel al-Qumisi was a faithful student of R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi. (See the book <i>Dod Mordekhai,</i><footnote id="164">This is a work by late seventeenth-century Eastern European Karaite Ḥakham Mordecai b. Nisan. It was reprinted by Yosef Algamil (Ramla, 1965).</footnote> folio 11b, where the author writes that Benjamin al-Nahawandi transmitted [the Karaite tradition] to Daniel al-Qumisi.<footnote id="165">Because Ḥakham Ṭoviyya is paraphrasing Ḥakham Mordecai b. Nisan, he uses the latter's spelling of “Qumiṣi,” with the letter <i>ẓadi</i> (Arabic <i>ṣad</i>), rather than the <i>samekh</i> that Babovich usually uses.</footnote>) However, he (= al-Qumisi) contradicted his teacher strongly on one point, namely, his opinion that God created an angel that created the universe (see my essay “Benjamin Nahawandi ha-Dayyan, son of the honorable Moses”).<footnote id="166">That is, the essay printed as the second part of <i>Rosh Pinna</i>. See above, ¶2.29-¶2.38, for a thorough discussion of this matter.</footnote> Not only did he endeavor to refute his teacher's opinion about the creation of this one angel, but he denied the existence of angels altogether, as we shall relate below.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.10</margin>He also often opposed the opinions of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, but only with respect to the branches and not the roots. This led some to slander him, saying that he who had originally referred to R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi as “the most enlightened” (<i>rosh ha-maskilim</i>) later referred to him as “the most foolish” (<i>rosh ha-kesilim</i>). R. Jacob al-Qirqisani (tenth century), in his <i>Book of Lights and Watchtowers</i>, part one, writes about this as follows: “It is an utter disgrace for such a wise and righteous man as R. Daniel al-Qumisi to say such a thing about R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>” (see Leon Nemoy's edition [New York, 1939], book 1, p. 5).</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.11</margin>This slander coupled with his denial of the existence of angels might have proved sufficient cause for later sages to refrain from including Daniel al-Qumisi's name on the memorial list of Jewish sages, whom the Karaites commemorate in their synagogues every Sabbath after the morning prayers.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.12</margin>R. Daniel al-Qumisi, like his distinguished teacher, wrote his works in Hebrew, and his language is pure and clear. He was also proficient in other languages and had full command of Arabic. The proof for this is that he not infrequently cites examples from Arabic to explain Hebrew words.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.13</margin>In books from the Cairo Geniza,<footnote id="167">The Cairo Geniza is a room in the Ben Ezra Synagogue in Cairo, where Jews disposed of holy books, and often many secular texts, because of reverence for anything written in the Hebrew alphabet. It was dramatically rediscovered by Solomon Schechter and other scholars in the late nineteenth century and has been a treasure trove of many otherwise unknown Jewish texts, as well as private letters, business documents, and all other sorts of ephemera. See Anita Hoffman and Peter Cole, <i>Sacred Trash: The Lost and Found World of the Cairo Geniza</i> (New York: Schocken Books, 2011).</footnote> there are references to his commentaries on the Pentateuch and on the books of Joshua and Judges, of which only fragments have reached us. From these fragments, we see that he did not write these commentaries verse by verse in the manner of the other exegetes but [commented] only on important or perplexing passages. On such passages, he wrote long comments, which shed light on the verse from every angle: from the religious point of view and the philosophic. The scholar Abraham Harkavy initially attributed these fragments to R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi but later retracted. <b>(See Appendix II.)</b></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.14</margin>We now cite the words of R. Daniel al-Qumisi on the creation of light and the human spirit, for they are very pleasing. On the creation of light, he writes:</p>

<quotation>Therefore, this axis (as in <i>the door is turning upon its axis</i> [Proverbs 26:14], here referring to the globe of the Earth) that we are on is the abode of darkness and gloom, as it is written: <i>Darkness was upon the face of the deep</i> (Genesis 1:2). Our Earth takes form<footnote id="168">In medieval Hebrew, the root <i>l-b-š</i>, literally meaning “to clothe,” is used philosophically to describe the assumption of form, materialization, or concretization.</footnote> upon the face of the deep, as we have explained,<footnote id="169">Vocalizing the Hebrew word as <i>kemo patarnu</i>, but it could be vocalized <i>kemo pitrono</i>, “according to its interpretation.”</footnote> and the darkness is entrenched on it as a permanent resident. But light is just passing through, entering through one gate and leaving through another. Darkness and gloom persist through night and day; it is only when the God of light<footnote id="170">Hebrew <i>eloah ha-or</i>, which can perhaps be translated as “God, who is the light.”</footnote> enters that the darkness and gloom flee, for the light comes and absorbs their form (that is, the darkness and gloom). They (= the darkness and gloom) cannot be seen in the light, only in a beclouded and concealed place. Light takes hold above, and darkness maintains its grip below. We see with our own eyes that it is so. It therefore says: <i>Darkness was upon the face of the deep</i>.</quotation>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.15</margin>Regarding the human spirit, he writes:</p>

<quotation>When he (that is: Adam) entered the Garden [of Eden], he was pure and pristine; but when he left, he was defiled by sin, much like the spirit, which is good and pleasant when drawn by the mouth into the body, but rank and foul when it leaves the body—it is transformed in an instant. Were this spirit not drawn in and respired, wafting through the body and preserving it, like the Spirit of God that hovered and protected the water of the deep, then the whole world, above and below, would disintegrate.</quotation>

<p indent="no">(See Jacob Mann, <i>Textes and Studies</i>, Vol. II, Karaitica, p. 12.)</p>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.16</margin>He also authored a <i>Book of Commandments</i>, which R. Yefet b. Ẓaʿir mentions; however, this book, too, has not come down to us in its entirety. Only a few passages and fragments have survived. The scholar Abraham Harkavy gathered all those passages and published them together with the remnant and relic<footnote id="171">Cf. Joshua 8:22.</footnote> of the <i>Book of Commandments</i> of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>. (See his <i>Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i>, Part II, pp. 187–192; and see my essay, “The Writings of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>.”)<footnote id="172">That is, the essay printed as the first part of <i>Rosh Pinna</i>. See above, ¶1.23-¶1.24.</footnote> This edition can be found here in the library of the Religious Court.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.17</margin>From these fragmentary passages, we can prove that his book included discussions of the sanctification of the New Moon; the Sabbath and the holidays; the forbidden and permitted; prohibited relations; the pure and impure; and more.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.18</margin>He also authored a book dedicated specifically to the laws of inheritance; this book, too, has not come down to us. The scholar Schechter<footnote id="173">Solomon Schechter (1847–1915) was an important scholar of Jewish texts and history, in England and the United States. He is credited with recognizing the value of the Cairo Geniza.</footnote> discovered a fragment of a manuscript in the Cairo Geniza, which discusses a dispute between Saʿadya Gaʾon the Pithomite<footnote id="174">Pithom is a place in Egypt mentioned in Exodus 1:11. Saʿadya was indeed from Egypt, but from Fayyūm. Some Karaites referred to Saʿadya as “the Pithomite” (see the poem by R. Israel b. Daniel ha-Dayyan of Alexandria cited below in ¶3.54). Perhaps “the Pithomite” is a misconstrual of “the Fayyūmite” (there is only one letter difference in Hebrew), or these Karaites may have believed that Pithom and Fayyūm were the same place.</footnote> and Daniel b. Moses, known by the epithet “al-Qumisi,” and which he<footnote id="175">The subject here is unclear. If it is Saʿadya, then the inference is that if Saʿadya wrote on inheritance law in reaction to al-Qumisi's work, then it stands to reason that al-Qumisi's work was also on inheritance law.</footnote> authored in order to illuminate the eyes of the nation regarding queries on the laws of inheritance.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.19</margin>In his Torah commentaries, he also expends effort answering the question that has taxed the minds of the true prophets and non-Jewish philosophers from time immemorial, namely: <i>Wherefore doth the way of the wicked prosper? Wherefore are all they secure that deal very treacherously?</i> (Jeremiah 12:1) Or, if we put it in the language of the ethicists: Why do we so often see in this world that “the righteous man has it bad, and the wicked man has it good?”<footnote id="176">This is a well-known quote from the Babylonian Talmud, <i>Berakhot</i> 7a.</footnote> Does this not attribute perversion of justice to God? His sole solution is to say that this world is the “place of deeds” and only the World to Come is the “place of retribution.”</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.20</margin>The works of R. Daniel al-Qumisi were at the disposal of many subsequent sages, but the ones who cite him most are our aforementioned teacher R. Jacob al-Qirqisani, in his book <i>The Lights and Watchtowers</i>, and R. Judah Hadassi, in his book <i>Eshkol ha-Kofer</i>, and after them, R. Aaron of Nicomedia, in his <i>Gan ʿEden</i>, R. Yefet b. Ẓaʿir, in his<i> Book of Commandments,</i> and R. Elijah Bašyachi, in his <i>Adderet Eliyyahu</i>.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.21</margin>We now quote some of the commentaries of R. Daniel al-Qumisi, as cited by R. Judah Hadassi in his <i>Eshkol ha-Kofer</i>:</p>

<quotation><margin side="right">¶3.22</margin><sc>Alphabet 126, Letter <i>Nun</i>:</sc><footnote id="177"><i>Eshkol ha-Kofer</i> is composed of numerous alphabetically acrostic passages of rhymed prose. This citation directs us to the 126th alphabetical acrostic, and within that to the passage beginning with the letter <i>nun</i>. The citations in the following paragraphs follow the same pattern.</footnote> In the Torah, it is written: <i>And He said unto Abram: Know of a surety that thy seed shall be a stranger in a land that is not theirs, and shall serve them; and they shall afflict them 400 years</i> (Genesis 15:13); but in another place, it is written: <i>Now the time that the children of Israel dwelt in Egypt was 430 years</i> (Exodus 12:40). He explains that we need to start the count [of 400 years] with the birth of Isaac, so that we end up with 400 years of Egyptian bondage.<footnote id="178">That is, the years of the Israelites “in Egypt” include not only their time spent there but all the time since the birth of Isaac. This is the approach in the ancient Rabbinic chronographic work <i>Seder ʿOlam</i>, attributed to the second-century sage R. Yosé b. Ḥalafta. For the relevant passage, in English translation, see Heinrich W. Guggenheimer, <i>Seder Olam:</i><i> The Rabbinic View of Biblical Chronology</i> (Northvale, NJ: Jason Aronson, 1998), p. 37ff. See above in ¶1.33, footnote 49.</footnote> As for the difference of 30 years between the two counts, he says that perhaps an extra 30 years were decreed upon them because they sinned in Egypt.

<margin side="right">¶3.23</margin><sc>Alphabet 233, Letter <i>Vav</i></sc>: He only permitted the consumption of fish eggs, not of bird eggs, because it is written in the Torah: <i>If a bird's nest chance to be before thee in the way, in any tree or on the ground, with young ones or eggs, and the dam sitting upon the young, or upon the eggs, thou shalt not take the dam with the young; thou shalt in any wise let the dam go, but the young thou mayest take unto thyself</i> (Deuteronomy 22:6–7). According to his opinion, the Torah here permits taking only the young but does not mention the eggs; therefore, the eggs are forbidden for consumption. However, he does permit fish eggs, based on the verse: <i>Every moving thing that liveth shall be for food for you</i> (Genesis 9:3), for, in his opinion, fish eggs are considered a “moving thing that liveth” and therefore are permitted, but bird eggs are considered a “moving thing that is dead” and therefore are forbidden.

<margin side="right">¶3.24</margin><sc>Alphabet 236, Letter <i>Zayin</i></sc>: Like our early sages—R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi, R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi, R. Sahl ha-Kohen, and R. Levi ha-Levi—he, too, forbids eating meat in the Exile,<footnote id="179">That is, in the period of exile, when the Temple is not standing; it applies even to someone who is physically in the Land of Israel.</footnote> relying on the verse: <i>And thou shalt offer thy burnt offerings, the flesh and the blood, upon the altar of the Lord thy God; and the blood of thy sacrifices shall be poured out against the altar of the Lord thy God, and thou shalt eat the flesh</i> (Deuteronomy 12:27). In their opinion, the flesh is permitted for consumption only after the animal's blood has been poured upon the altar, and since we currently do not have an altar upon which to pour its blood, consumption of meat is forbidden.

<margin side="right">¶3.25</margin><sc>Alphabet 240, Letter <i>Resh</i></sc>: In the Torah, it is written: <i>Thou shalt not seethe a kid (</i>gedi<i>) in the milk of its mother (</i>ʾimmo<i>)</i> (Exodus 23:19). There are some sages who interpret the word <i>gedi</i> here in the sense of “first fruits,” for they equate it to the word <i>meged</i>, which means “produce” or “fruit,”<footnote id="180">For a list of medieval commentators who took this approach, see Nahum M. Sarna, <i>The JPS Torah Commentary: Exodus</i> (Philadelphia and New York: Jewish Publication Society, 1991), p. 147.</footnote> and they interpret the word <i>ʾimmo</i> to mean <i>ʿimmo</i> (“with it”), as if it were written with an ʿ<i>ayin</i>. They say that in this verse, the Torah is forbidding the cooking of first fruits, or fruits, in milk. These exegetes come from the ranks of our Rabbanite brethren, who forbid the consumption of meat with milk.<footnote id="181">That is, although these commentators belong to the Rabbanite community and thus, as a matter of practical halakha, forbid eating meat with milk, they read the plain meaning of the verse as prohibiting something entirely different.</footnote> But R. Daniel al-Qumisi argues with them, saying that one should not interpret the verses of the Torah in a convoluted manner. The Torah here is forbidding the cooking of a kid in its mother's milk; there is no need to change the letters in order to invent whatever interpretation we want. It is clear from this verse that there is no prohibition against eating meat with milk, as long as the milk is not that of the [slaughtered animal's] mother.

<margin side="right">¶3.26</margin><sc>Alphabet 256, Letter <i>Nun</i></sc>: He also says (like some of our early sages) that if a man die,<footnote id="182">Cf. Numbers 27:8.</footnote> by whatever manner of death—whether [by illness] in bed, or by drowning in a river, or by strangulation, or by being hanged or killed by a court, or by being mortally poisoned, or by any circumstances that cause death in your world, and he passed away from the world, be it before or after his sons' death, and he left [grand]sons who issued from his loins, they shall inherit the entire estate of their paternal grandfather, as your wisdom deems befitting for sons. The parallel is when the daughters of Zelophehad inherited their father's portion, and it says, according to your Torah: <i>[If a man die,] and have no son, then ye shall cause his inheritance to pass unto his daughter</i> (Numbers 27:8). This means that a son takes precedence over a daughter and all of a son's descendants take precedence over those of a daughter.<footnote id="183">The Arabic continues with the following parenthetical: “(Based on this judicial ruling, the daughter of a dead man's son would have precedence over the dead man's daughter.)” This explanation does not appear in the Hebrew text of <i>Rosh Pinna</i>.</footnote>

<margin side="right">¶3.27</margin><sc>Alphabet 287, Letter <i>Gimel</i></sc>: Once the carcass of a pure animal has been made use of, it does not, by injunction,<footnote id="184">This word, like many in Hadassi's writing, is syntactically awkward and is placed here for the purpose of the rhyme.</footnote> render one who touches it impure. As it is said: <i>And the fat of that which dieth of itself, and the fat of that which is torn of beasts, may be used for any other service; but ye shall in no wise eat of it</i> (Leviticus 7:24) as food, for it has been rendered a carcass, out of its pure state. It says that it <i>may be used for any other service</i>, because its holiness has departed, and it says <i>ye shall in no wise eat of it</i>, as an injunction. [Thus], if you, for example, make soap out of its fat, it (= the soap) is not forbidden [to use].<b> (See Appendix III.)</b>

<margin side="right">¶3.28</margin><sc>Alphabet 316, Letter <i>Ḥet</i></sc>: He explains that the verse: <i>The nakedness of thy father, and the nakedness of thy mother, shalt thou not uncover</i> (Leviticus 18:7) does not refer to one's actual father and mother but to fraternal and sororal nieces. He says that they constitute the nakedness of one's father or mother and therefore are forbidden. Other sages disagreed with him and said that this verse refers to one's actual father and mother; that is, a daughter may not lie with her father and a son may not lie with his mother. They derive the prohibition concerning fraternal and sororal nieces from a different verse. They say that fraternal and sororal nieces are forbidden because the Torah forbids the <i>near of kin</i> (Leviticus 18:6)<i>,</i> and both the fraternal niece and sororal niece are <i>near of kin.</i> According to his opinion,<footnote id="185">The pronoun in “his opinion” is singular, so it would seem to refer to al-Qumisi. However, the way it is presented sounds more like the opinion of the opposing sages, for they derive the prohibition of lying with a niece from the term <i>near of kin</i>, which accords with the opinion presented in this sentence.</footnote> the Torah uses the term<i> kin</i> for the six nuclear relatives, namely, father, mother, son, daughter, brother, and sister, whereas the Torah uses the words <i>near of kin</i> to refer to the nuclear relatives of the nuclear relatives; for example, the father's father, mother's mother, father's brothers and sisters, mother's brothers and sisters, brother's sons and daughters, sister's sons and daughters, and the rest. <b>(See Appendix IV and Appendix V.)</b>

<margin side="right">¶3.29</margin><sc>Alphabet 373, Letter <i>Bet</i></sc>: Although R. Daniel al-Qumisi was a great Torah scholar, he was deficient in the natural sciences, as were most of our early sages; he did not advance any further in this discipline than did the Greek philosophers. Therefore, we see him, on occasion, struggle to explain his strange opinion about a certain natural phenomenon by citing verses from Scripture and interpreting them in a convoluted fashion. For instance, he subscribed to the view of those who maintain that all the [celestial] spheres<footnote id="186">Hebrew <i>galgalim</i>, corresponding to the Latin <i>sphaerae</i>; according to late antique and medieval astronomical understanding, these are enormous clear spherical containers, which cause the motion of the planets and other celestial bodies.</footnote> (that is, the luminaries) are sentient beings; so he asks: how is it that they constantly revolve and move, yet do not close their eyes to rest—for is there such a thing in the world that is sentient but never rests? Daniel al-Qumisi says that there is a certain bird in the Land of Edom that constantly flies and is alert and neither alights nor rests, and it was to this creature that righteous Job (peace be upon him) alluded when he said <i>Doth the hawk soar by thy wisdom, and stretch her wings toward the south (</i>teman<i>)?</i><footnote id="187">Qumisi probably reads the word <i>teman</i> not to mean “south” but rather as referring to a place in Edom, seeing as one of the Edomite clans is named “Teman” (Genesis 36:15).</footnote> (Job 39:26).

<margin side="right">¶3.29.1</margin>Other exegetes say that this wondrous bird's name is <i>ḥol</i>, also mentioned in Job: <i>and I shall multiply my days as the phoenix (</i>ḥol<i>)</i> (Job 29:18). Some commentators say that the name of this mythical bird is <i>nesher</i>.<footnote id="188">The biblical <i>nesher</i> is typically understood to be a vulture or eagle.</footnote> They relate that this mythical <i>nesher</i> lives a very long time, up to 500 or 1,000 years, and then when it senses its end has come,<footnote id="189">Cf. Lamentations 4:18.</footnote> the bird soars toward the sun, which incinerates it and turns it into ash, from the heaps of which is revealed or born a little <i>nesher</i> chick, which similarly lives a very long time and at the end of its life does as its parent did, and so on until the end of time. According to their opinion, this verse is referring to this wondrous <i>nesher</i>: <i>thy youth is renewed like the</i> nesher (Psalms 103:5). A legend about such a wondrous bird is also found among the peoples of Europe, who call it the “phoenix,” and the mythology of Arab tribes includes tales of such a wondrous bird, which they call <i>abābīl</i>.</quotation>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.30</margin>R. Daniel al-Qumisi says that we should not act according to the customs that our ancestors practiced prior to the giving of the Torah.<footnote id="190">That is, if the Torah later prohibited these actions.</footnote> For example:</p>

<quotation>1. <margin side="right">¶3.31</margin>A man may not marry his aunt, even though Amram, father of Moses (peace be upon him), married his aunt.

2. <margin side="right">¶3.32</margin>A man may not marry his brother's wife, even though Judah's son Onan married the wife of his brother, Er.

3. <margin side="right">¶3.33</margin>A man may not marry two sisters, even though Jacob (peace be upon him) married two sisters, Rachel and Leah. For all these were [permissible only] because they occurred before the giving of the Torah.</quotation>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.34</margin>We have drawn all this information about R. Daniel al-Qumisi from the book <i>Eshkol ha-Kofer</i>. Now we shall add some more of his interpretations, which we draw from other sources:</p>

<quotation>1. <margin side="right">¶3.35</margin>R. Daniel al-Qumisi also affirms and maintains the law of visual sighting [of the moon], just as R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i> did.<footnote id="191">See above in ¶1.29.</footnote> Since our Muslim brethren likewise observe the law of sanctifying the months on the basis of visual sighting, and the conditions for sanctification are the same for us and them, he rules admissible the testimony of our Muslim brethren regarding the sighting of the moon.

2. <margin side="right">¶3.36</margin>He forbids doing work on the Sabbath, not only by means of a Jewish servant but also by means of a non-Jewish servant, and with no difference between a servant who is a day laborer or a servant [or slave] for a fixed period of time.

3. <margin side="right">¶3.37</margin>He forbids leaving the boundary (<i>teḥum</i>) of the city not only on the Sabbath but also on the holidays, because, in his view, the sanctity of the holidays is equal to the sanctity of the Sabbath. He says that although we find that the Israelites departed Egypt on the fifteenth of Nisan (that is, on the Festival of Matzah), we cannot derive from this a permit to leave the boundary of the city on the holidays, for the Exodus from Egypt occurred before the giving of the Torah, when God commanded us to sanctify the Sabbath [and the holidays].

4. <margin side="right">¶3.38</margin>He says about the Festival of Shavuot that we are obligated to sanctify it, without question, on Sunday, and that it is forbidden to sanctify it on any other day of the week. As it is written in the Torah:<i> And ye shall count unto you from morrow after the Sabbath,</i><footnote id="192">See above in ¶1.31, footnote 46.</footnote><i> from the day that ye brought the sheaf of the waving; seven Sabbaths shall there be complete; even unto the morrow after the seventh Sabbath shall ye number 50 days; and ye shall present a new meal offering unto the Lord</i> (Leviticus 23:15–16)—for the words <i>morrow after the Sabbath</i> refer to Sunday, and not to any other day of the week.

5. <margin side="right">¶3.39</margin>Regarding the Festival of Sukkot, he says that we are obligated to adorn the sukkah that we make with all sorts of nice, beautiful fruits. He says that what is written in the Torah—<i>And ye shall take you on the first day the fruit of goodly trees (</i>peri ʿeẓ hadar<i>)</i> (Leviticus 23:40)—means a date, and he buttresses his words from the verse: <i>This thy stature is like to a palm tree</i> (Song of Songs 7:8). This is in opposition to those, namely, our Rabbanite brethren, who say that the meaning of <i>peri ʿeẓ hadar</i> is a fruit that dwells (<i>haddar</i>) on its tree, such as the citron, which is found on the tree year-round. But grammar precludes this latter interpretation, for the word <i>hadar</i> means “beautiful” [or] “comely,” and if the intent of <i>hadar</i> were “that which dwells,” it would need to be written <i>haddar</i> (with a doubled <i>dalet</i>), not <i>hadar</i>.

6. <margin side="right">¶3.40</margin>He forbids the consumption of both domesticated and undomesticated mammals in the Exile, for the reason that in the Exile we do not possess an altar on which to sprinkle the blood (see Leviticus, chapter 17). And of the fowl, he only permits turtledoves and young pigeons (which are called <i>sumān</i> and <i>ḥamām</i> in Arabic). He says that although the Torah explicitly forbids only 21 species of birds, which are mentioned in Deuteronomy 14:11–18, all other species being permitted, nonetheless, because we have forgotten the language of our Torah, we can no longer ascertain beyond doubt the exact translations of the 21 names of the impure birds, so out of concern that we might err, we may eat only the two aforementioned species, for which we have a tradition transmitted generation after generation that they are pure and permitted for consumption.

7. <margin side="right">¶3.41</margin>According to his opinion, only four types of locusts are permitted for consumption, and these are the ones mentioned in the Torah: <i>arbé</i>, <i>solʿam</i>, <i>ḥargol</i>, and <i>ḥagav</i>.<footnote id="193">See Leviticus 11:22. The precise identification of these species of locusts, grasshoppers, and crickets remains uncertain; see above in ¶2.26, footnote 27. </footnote>

8. <margin side="right">¶3.42</margin>R. Daniel al-Qumisi was a proponent of <i>rikkuv</i>;<footnote id="194">For more on <i>rikkuv</i>, see above, ¶1.24 and ¶2.18 with footnotes.</footnote> he forbade all relatives of the wife to all relatives of the husband, because, according to him, a husband and wife are considered one body, as it is written: <i>Therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother, and shall cleave unto his wife, and they shall be one flesh</i> (Genesis 2:24).

9. <margin side="right">¶3.43</margin>Regarding what it says in the Torah, <i>And thou shalt not take a woman to her sister, to be a rival to her, to uncover her nakedness, beside the other in her lifetime</i> (Leviticus 18:18), he says that this refers to a stepsister and not to a true biological one; he says that marrying the true sister of one's wife is forbidden always, as we learn by inference from comparing similar language (<i>heqqesh gezera shava</i>) from the verse: <i>Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy brother's wife: it is thy brother's nakedness</i> (Leviticus 18:16)—and if it is always forbidden for two brothers to marry the same woman, so must it always be forbidden for two sisters to marry the same man. However, marrying the stepsister of one's wife is only forbidden during her lifetime, so that there will not be rivalry between them, but after the wife dies, he is permitted to marry her stepsister, because rivalry is no longer an issue.

10. <margin side="right">¶3.44</margin>It should be noted here that R. Daniel al-Qumisi says that the beginning of the new year (<i>rosh ha-shana</i>) is not the first of Tishri, which is the appointed <i>yom teruʿa</i>,<footnote id="195"><i>Yom teruʿa</i> is the term used in Numbers 29:1 to describe the holiday on the first day of Tishri, which most Jews today call “Rosh Hashanah.” Most Karaites, both historically and today, have interpreted <i>yom teruʿa</i> as “a day of shouting” in prayer, whereas Rabbanites interpret it as “a day of blowing the shofar.” As far as I am aware, Qumisi is unique among Karaite authorities in that he advocates blowing the shofar on the <i>yom teruʿa</i>. He says that the shofar can serve to awaken the people to repentance, though it is unclear whether he believes that shofar-blowing is actually a commandment inherent in the Torah's words <i>yom teruʿa</i>. See Mordecai b. Nisan<i>, Royal Attire</i>, pp. 185–186.</footnote> as it is for us nowadays; rather, it is on the tenth of Tishri, which is Yom Kippur. We see that perhaps he is correct, for it is written in the Torah very clearly: <i>Then shalt thou make proclamation with the blast of the horn on the tenth day of the seventh month;</i><footnote id="196">The seventh month is Tishri, for Scripture counts the months from Nisan, but the new year can still begin in Tishri, as years follow a different cycle.</footnote><i> in the day of atonement shall ye make proclamation with the horn throughout all your land. Consecrate the fiftieth year</i> (Leviticus 25:9–10).</quotation>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.45</margin>In the beginning of this essay, we mentioned the fact that R. Daniel al-Qumisi did not believe in the existence of angels, and now we will elucidate his opinion in detail.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.46</margin>R. Daniel al-Qumisi did not believe in the existence of angels in the world—spiritual beings with the faculty of speech like humans, which God dispatches over the Earth to carry out His orders—because the creation of angels is not mentioned in the narrative of the six days of Creation nor anywhere else in the Torah. And even though a small number of sages said that the angels were created on the first day, they do not have anything on which to rely.<footnote id="197">Cf. Mishna, <i>Sotah</i> 9:15.</footnote> R. Daniel al-Qumisi interprets the [Scriptural] terms <i>malʾakh</i> and <i>malʾakhim</i> to refer to forces of nature [instead of angels]. He says that all forces of nature—such as wind, fire, cloud, earthquake, rain—all are considered the agents of God. Similarly, all the tribulations and suffering that befall a person are also God's agents carrying out His orders, to reorient man to the paths of righteousness. He supports his opinion with verses from Scripture, and these are they: <i>Who makest winds Thy messengers (</i>malʾakhim<i>), the flaming fire Thy ministers</i> (Psalms 104:4). <i>He sent forth upon them the fierceness of His anger, wrath, and indignation, and trouble, a sending of messengers (</i>malʾakhim<i>) of evil</i> (Psalms 78:49). And he says that there is another verse, in which the pillar of cloud is called a <i>malʾakh</i>: <i>And the messenger (</i>malʾakh<i>) of God, who went before the camp of Israel, removed and went behind them; and the pillar of cloud removed from before them, and stood behind them</i> (Exodus 14:19).</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.47</margin>Even if, on occasion, we see in Scripture that angels are mentioned by name, [such as] “Gabriel” or “Michael,” R. Daniel al-Qumisi says that they were created only temporarily with their forms, appearing in various forms to the prophets, according to the needs of the moment—sometimes they appeared girded in weapons, if the occasion was one of anger and doom; at other times as a hoary old man, if the occasion was one of good will and beneficent providence. (See the book<i> Qol Yehuda</i>, letter <i>hé</i> in the prayer book for Yom Kippur by R. Isaac b. Solomon, author of <i>Or ha-Levana</i>.)</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.48</margin>The Rabbanite scholar Samuel Poznański (may his soul rest in Eden) says that R. Daniel al-Qumisi endeavored with this opinion of his not only to refute the opinion of his teacher, R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi, which we mentioned above, but also to align with that of the Sadducean sect, which categorically denied the existence of angels, as is mentioned in the Evangelion (= the New Testament): <i>For the Sadducees say that there is no resurrection, neither angel, nor spirit: but the Pharisees confess both</i> (Acts of the Apostles 23:8).<footnote id="198">King James translation.</footnote> <b>(See Appendix VI.)</b></p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.49</margin>We see fit to conclude this essay by mentioning that R. Judah Hadassi, in his <i>Eshkol ha-Kofer</i>, calls R. Daniel al-Qumisi “enlightened” (<i>maskili</i>), just as he calls our other sages, and he means this in the sense of “Karaite,” for he always refers to the Karaites as “enlightened ones” (<i>maskilim</i>). In his opinion, this verse in Daniel refers to the Karaites: <i>And they that are wise (</i>ha-maskilim<i>) shall shine as the brightness of the firmament; and they that turn the many to righteousness as the stars for ever and ever</i> (Daniel 12:3).</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.50</margin>Our purpose in mentioning this is [to demonstrate] that the great sage R. Judah Hadassi, who was very punctilious in carrying out the Torah's commandments, considered R. Daniel al-Qumisi a full-fledged Karaite, even though he deviates, in some of his interpretations, from the interpretations of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>, which is in accordance with the freedom that was granted by R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi himself to anyone who believes in the Torah, for he said: “Search Scripture well, and do not rely on my opinion.” This is our retort to the minority of scholars who are inclined to say that R. Daniel al-Qumisi crossed the line of the Karaite faith, which is an error on their part.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.51</margin>We should also note here, once we are on the matter, that R. Judah Hadassi also refers to the Karaites as “goodly figs,” because he opines that the following verse refers to the Karaites: <i>One basket had very good figs, like the figs that are first ripe</i> (Jeremiah 24:2). R. Salmon b. Yeruḥim (may his soul rest in Eden), R. [Jacob b.] Reuben the author of <i>Sefer ha-ʿOsher</i>, and our other sages refer to the Karaites as <i>shoshannim</i> (lilies), because they are of the opinion that words such as “lilies,” “buds,” and the like, which appear in Song of Songs and other books of Scripture, are epithets for the righteous, and the righteous, according to them, are the Karaites, since only the Karaites follow the straight path in interpreting the Torah and its commandments. We should also mention here that even non-Jewish scholars admit that the Karaites have kept the Torah of Moses in its pristine state, veering neither to the right nor to the left,<footnote id="199">Cf. Numbers 20:17.</footnote> and we hope to discuss this in a dedicated essay, with God's help.</p>

<h1><margin side="right">¶3.52</margin>Appendix I [On R. Israel b. Daniel ha-Dayyan of Alexandria]</h1>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.53</margin>Some scholars say that R. Israel b. Daniel ha-Dayyan of Alexandria was the son of R. Daniel al-Qumisi, but this is incorrect, because Israel lived in the year 4822 from Creation (1062 CE), while R. Daniel al-Qumisi lived in the ninth century CE. Nevertheless, it is possible that R. Israel ha-Dayyan was a descendant of R. Daniel al-Qumisi. Evidence of this is the fact that R. Moses Bašyachi, in his book <i>Zevaḥ Pesaḥ</i>, calls him “Israel al-Qumisi of the sages of Dusṭar.”</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.54</margin>Once we have mentioned the name of R. Israel b. Daniel ha-Dayyan of Alexandria, we will add a bit more worth noting. He was the one who authored a <i>Book of Commandments</i>, and he is the one who wrote the polemical poem that begins: “The erring Pithomite has come, / he and Samuel the child of Ḥofni, / to uproot the faith of the Scripturalists, / as the son of the North has plotted.” [This was aimed] against two <i>geʾonim</i> from [the Academy of] Sura in Babylonia: R. Saʿadya b. Joseph Gaʾon, who is called by the Karaite sages “Saʿadya of Fayyum” (the most famous <i>gaʾon</i> of the Suran <i>geʾonim</i>; d. 942) and R. Samuel b. Ḥofni (who was a priest, according to the scholar Abraham Firkovich, the last <i>gaʾon</i> of Sura, d. 1034).</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.55</margin>This poem has been printed twice. The first time, it was printed with omissions and lines out of order in the scholar R. Simḥa Pinsker's<i> Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i>, pp. 174-176. The second time, it was published correctly and in full with commentary by the scholar and researcher R. Abraham Firkovich in his <i>Bené Reshef</i>, pp. 3-12, published in Vienna in the year 5631 from Creation, which corresponds to 1871 CE.</p>

<h1><margin side="right">¶3.56</margin>Appendix II [On Yashar of Candia]</h1>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.57</margin>It is also appropriate to note here that the commentary of R. Daniel al-Qumisi (may his soul rest in Eden) on the book of Genesis was rescued from the teeth of time thanks to the noted philosopher and physician R. Joseph Solomon Delmedigo, who is known as “Yashar of Candia,”<footnote id="200">Heb. <i>yashar</i>, literally, “straight,” is an acronym (YaShaR) for “Yosef Shelomo ha-Rofé”; that is, “Joseph Solomon the Physician.”</footnote> since he was born on Candia (the island known today as “Crete”) to his father, the sage R. Elijah, in the year 1591, and passed away in Prague in 1655.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.58</margin>This great man, from the ranks of our Rabbanite brethren, had ties with some Karaite sages; therefore, we shall devote some words to his biography. He studied at the University of Padua in Italy, where he learned mathematics and astronomy in depth, under the tutelage of the great Galileo Galilei.<footnote id="201">The Hebrew text reverses the order of his personal name and surname.</footnote> He was fond of traveling in various lands, and he was a lover of books (a bibliophile);<footnote id="202">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya writes “Bibliofil” in Latin characters.</footnote> he collected many works of Karaite sages for his library, and he expressed great admiration for Karaite sages and their literature.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.59</margin>He spent time in Poland and Lithuania<footnote id="203">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya uses the Russian name for Lithuania, “Litva.”</footnote> and, for a time, served as personal physician to Prince Radziwiłł of Lithuania, in the city of Vilna. While there, he became known to the Karaite <i>ḥakham</i> of the city of Trakai, R. Zeraḥ b. Nathan of Trakai (born in Trakai in 1580), and became good friends with him. R. Zeraḥ of Trakai posed 12 questions to Yashar in the fields of mathematics, astronomy, natural science, and chemistry, and he requested of him to resolve 70 difficulties for him in these various disciplines. As a response to these questions, Yashar composed his book known as <i>Elim</i>, after the verse: <i>And they came to Elim, where were 12 springs of water and 70 palm trees; and they encamped there by the waters</i> (Exodus 15:27).</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.60</margin>When Yashar found himself in Egypt during one of his sojourns, in order to seek out rare books, he became known to the <i>ḥakham</i> of the Karaites in Cairo, namely, R. Jacob Iskandari, whose name is mentioned in the fourth table, among the names of sages the Karaites commemorate every Sabbath after the conclusion of the morning prayers. R. Jacob Iskandari wrote treatises on the questions that appear in the first six chapters of the work of the famous astronomer Euclid. At his request, Yashar composed a work on mechanics.<footnote id="204">Ḥakham Ṭoviyya uses the French <i>mécanique</i>.</footnote> Yashar effusively praises the wisdom of R. Jacob Iskandari, and he writes the following about him in his <i>Iggeret ha-Aḥuz</i>, (which we shall mention below): “In the city of Cairo, Egypt I saw a unique individual, exalted and lofty with bravery, the honorable R. Jacob Iskandari, a wise man learned<footnote id="205">Cf. Deuteronomy 4:6.</footnote> in the disciplines. He made his own small contribution<footnote id="206">Cf. Babylonian Talmud, <i>Qiddushin</i> 48b.</footnote> to Euclid's book: he explained the forms in Euclid's book with geometrical proofs.”</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.61</margin>The lengthy letter that Yashar dispatched to his close friend, R. Zeraḥ of Trakai, is well known in the literary world. Literary scholars call this the <i>Iggeret Aḥuz</i> (because it begins with the words: “Bound [<i>aḥuz</i>] by the fetters of the vanities of the Earth's inhabitants, mourning and moaning between the bushes”). This letter was published along with the book <i>Pinnat Yiqrat</i> by R. Isaac b. Solomon, the author of<i> Or ha-Levana</i>, in the year 5594 from Creation (1834 CE), in the city of Gozlov, on the Crimean Peninsula in Russia. The scholar Abraham Geiger translated it into German and published [the Hebrew text] again accompanied by the translation in his <i>Melo Ḥofnayim</i>, in 1840. In this letter, the sage Yashar lists all the books that he wrote, and they are a great many. He likewise lists all the rare books he was able to acquire during his many travels. Above, we mentioned that he held the Karaite sages and their works in high regard, and in the <i>Iggeret Aḥuz</i>, he writes thus in various places: “‘Know the face of your flock, and set your heart to the flocks’ (Proverbs 27:23), the two golden spouts<footnote id="207">Cf. Zechariah 4:12.</footnote>: the Karaite rabbis [named] Aaron.” He is referencing here R. Aaron I the Physician, author of <i>[Sefer] ha-Mivḥar</i><footnote id="208"><i>Sefer ha-Mivḥar</i> is a well-known Karaite commentary on the Torah. Several later Karaite sages have composed supercommentaries on it, the most famous of which is <i>Ṭirat Kesef</i> by Ḥakham Joseph Lutzki (Gozlov, 1835).</footnote> (thirteenth century), and R. Aaron the Latter of Nicomedia (fourteenth century), author of ʿ<i>Eẓ Ḥayyim</i>,<i> Keter Tora</i>, and <i>Gan ʿEden</i>.</p>

<p>Additionally, he writes there: “In this lofty tier of the exposition of Scripture, I include the Karaite exegetes such as R. Jacob [b. Reuben], author of <i>Sefer ha-ʿOsher</i> (eleventh century), as well as [the authors of] <i>Sefer ha-Mivḥar</i> and <i>Sefer Keter Tora</i>. Everything they expounded on verses from the Prophets and the Writings are completely clear, fully satisfying, and close to the plain meaning [of Scripture]. The second tier consists of Radaq's<footnote id="209">R. David Qimḥi (1160–1235), known by the acronym “Radaq,” lived in Narbonne, Provence (today southern France). In addition to writing an extensive commentary on most of Scripture, he is also considered to be one of the foremost Hebrew grammarians.</footnote> commentary, and the third tier comprises Rashi's<footnote id="210">R. Solomon b. Isaac (1040–1105), known by the acronym “Rashi,” lived in Troyes, France. He is widely considered the foremost Rabbanite exegete on both the Bible and the Talmud.</footnote> commentary on the 24 books [of Scripture]…”</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.62</margin>We must bear in mind that Radaq and Rashi are the chief exegetes among our Rabbanite brethren, yet R. Yashar of Candia places the Karaite exegetes on a higher level than them, for his words utter the uprightness of his heart, and that which his lips know, they speak sincerely.<footnote id="211">Cf. Job 33:3. There is a play on words here, since “uprightness” is a translation of <i>yosher</i>, which has the same Hebrew consonants as Yashar.</footnote> (See the introduction of the sage R. Judah Sawaskan<footnote id="212">R. Judah b. Isaac Sawaskan was a Crimean sage who flourished in the nineteenth century. The introductory pages to his edition of <i>Keter Tora</i> are not numbered; his citation of Yashar of Candia is on the second page of the section “Haqdamat ha-Maggiah ve-ha-Moẓi la-Or.”</footnote> to R. Aaron the Younger of Nicomedia's <i>Keter Tora</i>, which he published in Gozlov in 1866.)</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.63</margin>It pains me greatly that I have nothing to add to the biography of the sage R. Jacob Iskandari, who merited the spiritual honor of being included among the great sages commemorated every Sabbath in our synagogues and whose wisdom is praised by such a dear philosopher and scholar as Yashar of Candia. But there is no one among us who knows about his career or can say where his works have gone, and I cannot even tell the dates of his birth or death. Only this do we know for certain: he lived at the same time as Yashar of Candia (that is, in the seventeenth century). More than that, we do not know.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.64</margin>In the book of Proverbs, King Solomon (peace be upon him) says: <i>and a word in due season, how good is it!</i> (Proverbs 15:23). I find it fitting to mention here what I have written in my article, which was published in our annual calendar for the year 5704 from Creation. I wrote there (in the Hebrew on p. 17, and in the Arabic on p. 34) that there must be a sage,<footnote id="213">After the word <i>ḥakham</i>, “scholar,” Babovich's text reads <i>ḥanna</i> or <i>ḥinna</i>; it is unclear what this word is supposed to mean, and it may be a printing error. In Aramaic, <i>ḥinna</i> means “charm” or “grace.”</footnote> an individual designated to preserve the ancient books and old manuscripts in an archive,<footnote id="214">Babovich writes the Hebrew word <i>geniza</i>, and then, in Latin characters and in parentheses, “Archiv,” to clarify that this is not the type of <i>geniza</i> in which texts are merely discarded haphazardly.</footnote> so that these rare and priceless artifacts not become moth-eaten, moldy, etc. I will now add a few more words—a little balm and a little honey<footnote id="215">Cf. Genesis 43:11.</footnote>—on this important matter.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.65</margin>I will begin by saying that we must have a designated library of several rooms in which we can gather all the books and documents, whether printed or in manuscript, written by Karaites or by others about Karaites, from every country on Earth and in every language.<footnote id="216">This lofty vision of Ḥakham Ṭoviyya is yet to see its full completion, but a great start has been made with the recent publication of the monumental <i>Bibliographica Karaitica</i>, which endeavors to list every single work published (in every language) by and about Karaites. See Barry Dov Walfish with Mikhail Kizilov<i>, Bibliographia Karaitica: An Annotated Bibliography of Karaites and Karaism</i> (Leiden and Boston: Brill, 2011).</footnote> Then, whoever wishes to acquire not superficial but deep, factual knowledge of Karaites in general, and of Karaite literature in particular, from their very beginning, that is, from the days of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi (eighth century) until today, can come to this palace, the palace of Karaite wisdom, and find whatever it is they seek about it.</p>

<quotation>I. <margin side="right">¶3.66</margin>In my opinion, all the printed books and manuscripts to be collected in this palace should be organized according to when they were put to parchment by their authors or copyists; in other words, they should be organized chronologically, such that for every century there should be one, two, or more bookcases in the following order: eighth century, ninth century, tenth century, eleventh century, and so on. All these books and manuscripts should be listed in a special catalog, which will be called the “Catalog by Era” or “Chronological Catalog.”

II. <margin side="right">¶3.67</margin>After that, we should make another catalog in which to list all the books and manuscripts according not to their date of composition but their place of composition. For instance, the Karaite sages in Egypt and their works; the Karaite sages in the Land of Israel and their works; the Karaite sages in Babylonia and their works; the Karaite sages in Spain and their works; the Karaite sages in Turkey and their works; the Karaite sages from the Kingdom of the Tatars on the Crimean Peninsula and their works; the Karaite sages from Russia and their works; the Karaite sages from Lithuania and Poland and their works; and so forth. This catalog should be labeled the “Regional” or “Geographical Catalog.”

III. <margin side="right">¶3.68</margin>Next, we should make one special catalog in which the names of all the Karaite sages, and the titles of their works, are listed in alphabetical order, so as to make it easier for researchers trying to locate them; and another special catalog in which to record the names of all the non-Jewish scholars who wrote about the Karaites—this, too, according to alphabetical order. These catalogs should be called the “Alphabetical Catalogs.”

IV. <margin side="right">¶3.69</margin>After all these, we will be able to make more catalogs, in which we will list the names of our sages who worked in a particular area of scholarship. For example, we shall write thus: “On Biblical exegesis, the following sages of ours wrote: R. Jacob b. Reuben, and the name of his book is <i>Sefer ha-ʿOsher</i>; R. Aaron I, and the name of his book is <i>Sefer ha-Mivḥar</i>; R. Aaron II of Nicomedia, and the name of his book is <i>Keter Tora</i>; and so forth.”

“On the Exposition of the Commandments, the following sages of ours wrote: R. Benjamin al-Nahawandi, and the name of his book is <i>Sefer ha-Dinim</i> or <i>Masʾat Binyamin</i>; R. Aaron II of Nicomedia, and the name of his exposition is <i>Gan ʿEden</i>; R. Elijah Bašyachi, and the name of his book is <i>Adderet Eliyyahu</i>; and so forth.”

For every particular discipline and field, we should make a special catalog of the names of all the Karaite sages who wrote about it and the title of their works in this field. Each of these catalogs should be labeled with a distinctive title, such as “Catalog of the Field of Grammatical Studies”; “Catalog of the Field of Linguistic Studies” (that is, the lexicons); “Catalog of the Field of Biblical Exegesis”; and so forth.</quotation>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.70</margin>When I brought the matter before my friend Mr. Kadar b. Yefet Massouda (of blessed memory),<footnote id="217">He lived 1885–1965. He served as chairman of the Karaite Religious Council; see Algamil, <i>Karaite Jewry</i>, English section, p. 79.</footnote> the dignified chairman of our National Committee, he agreed with my suggestions in good cheer, exclaiming to me: Dignified Ḥakham! Everything you have said is all well and good, but before doing this, before we purchase the books, we must prepare a proper space for them, that is, a building of several rooms where we can store the bookcases and crates with these books.</p>

<p>At which point I responded to his eminence: Dignified chairman! Your Eminence has spoken logically, and I will continue in this vein, with similar logic: Your Eminence says that the rooms must come before the books, which is true, but there is something that comes even before the rooms.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.71</margin>And when his eminence asked me: What is it that would need to come before the rooms, before the building of the Palace of Karaite Wisdom? I responded to his eminence: “Money, money, and more money!” We both had a good laugh, as did our friend, his brother ʿAbbas b. Yefet Massouda, a member of the National Committee who was with us at the time.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.72</margin>Truth be told, there are many things that our community lacks, and we cannot cover them out of the community's coffers; just as the sea cannot become full if the rivers do not flow into it,<footnote id="218">Cf. Ecclesiastes 1:7.</footnote> so too the community chest cannot be filled unless the members of the community contribute a small portion of the income that God has granted them. The takeaway from the foregoing is that it is up to us to fulfill the commandments of our holy Torah and take a tithe of our wealth and give it as a donation to the Lord, whereby the whole deficit of our community will be made whole. Then, the light of our community will shine like a bright star on the horizon of beautiful Egypt<footnote id="219">Cf. Jeremiah 46:20.</footnote> (may God preserve it, Amen), among the other communities that flourish under the good governance of our mighty and beloved King Farouk I, may he live forever, Amen.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.73</margin>See my article titled <i>Maʿaser</i> (“Tithe”), which was published in our annual calendar for the year 1942, pp. 7ff. in Hebrew and pp. 15ff. in Arabic. Go read it!<footnote id="220">Cf. Jonah 1:6.</footnote></p>

<h1><margin side="right">¶3.74</margin>Appendix III [On the Laws of Impurity Contracted from the Dead in the Exile]</h1>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.75</margin>R. Daniel al-Qumisi opposes the other sages, who maintain that there is no corpse impurity in the Exile, and R. Jacob al-Qirqisani attests that this was also the opinion of R. ʿAnan ha-Nasi <i>yrʺe</i>. This is because the way to purify one who has contracted corpse impurity is with water mixed with ashes of the Red Heifer (see Numbers 19), but in exile, we do not have access to this ash water, and they say that one cannot become impure unless there is some method of purification (whether by fire, wind, or water). So, if we deem [someone] impure by corpse impurity but cannot provide them with a way to be purified, because one who has contracted corpse impurity does not become pure through [mere] water as other [kinds of] impure people do, we would remain [forever] impure, and, accordingly, would not be able to pray or read or touch sacred Scripture.<footnote id="221">The universal Rabbanite position is that, indeed, in our day, when there is no access to the ashes of the Red Heifer, anyone who comes in contact with a corpse contracts its impurity, which remains on them for their whole lives. However, Rabbanite law does not forbid impure people from praying or touching holy books but only from eating most sacrifices and some other holy foods and from entering certain parts of the Temple Mount.</footnote> However, we find that Scripture commands us to pray in the Exile, as it is written: <i>and go, and pray</i> (Jeremiah 29:12); and it is written: <i>and pray unto Thee toward their land</i> (I Kings 8:48). (See <i>Adderet Eliyyahu</i>, Seder Tumʾa ve-Tahara, Chapter 19.)</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.76</margin>But most Karaite sages maintain that there is ritual impurity in the Exile, except that the commandments were given in accordance with the capacity [to observe them]. Therefore, although R. Daniel al-Qumisi concurs with the sages who maintain that ritual impurity exists in the Exile, nonetheless, he is not overly stringent about this commandment. According to him, only the vessel that comes in direct contact with the source of impurity becomes impure, not any other vessel that comes into contact with the source of impurity by way of other vessels. For if we do not maintain this, then there would be no end to it, and every vessel in Jerusalem would be impure if it had come into contact, via a chain [of contacts], with vessels in Baghdad! He adduces proof from the Torah for his opinion: <i>This is the law: when a man dieth in a tent, every one that cometh into the tent, and every thing that is in the tent, shall be unclean seven days. And every open vessel, which hath no covering close-bound upon it, is unclean</i> (Numbers 19:14–15). The explanation is that even the severest degree of impurity, which is corpse impurity that contaminates by contact, is only if a vessel has no close-bound covering on it; so how could it possibly confer impurity to vessels that never came into direct contact with it?</p>

<h1><margin side="right">¶3.77</margin>Appendix IV [On the Laws of Forbidden Marriages]</h1>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.78</margin>R. Yefet the Physician b. David b. Samuel b. Ẓaʿir (thirteenth century), who is known in Arabic as <i>al-Ḥakīm al-Ṣafī</i> (“the expert physician”), composed his <i>Book of Commandments</i> in ten sections, which was translated into Hebrew by Ḥakham Samuel Kohen b. R. Solomon Kohen of Damascus, in honor of Moses Çelebi Sinani II (see Appendix V, on the Çelebi family), in the year 5482 from Creation (1722 CE). In the ninth section of the book, which discusses the laws of incest, he quotes a complete excerpt from Daniel al-Qumisi, which we reproduce here in full, on account of its great importance. This is what he says:</p>

<quotation>R. Daniel al-Qumisi (may his soul rest in Eden) learned from this verse—<i>And thou shalt not take a woman to her sister, to be a rival to her, to uncover her nakedness, beside the other in her lifetime</i> (Leviticus 18:18)—that the daughter of the wife of one's father-in-law is forbidden, saying that all this is derived via <i>heqqesh</i> (inference)<i>.</i> When it happens<footnote id="222">The meaning of Hebrew <i>yaʿavor</i> here is not entirely certain. In addition to its usual meanings, in Karaite usage, the root <i>ʿ-b-r</i> has the additional meanings of “to occur” and “to permit.” See Eliezer Ben-Yehuda, <i>A Complete Dictionary of Ancient and Modern Hebrew</i> (Laʿam, 1948–1959), p. 4284, col. a.</footnote> to stipulate about them, saying: <i>beside the other in her lifetime</i>, it happens to stipulate it (also) about a true sister. And these are the words of Daniel al-Qumisi (may his soul rest in Eden) in his <i>Book of Commandments</i>: “If your wife should have a sister born from the wife of your father-in-law, or she (= the sister) is the daughter of the husband of your mother-in-law, and she was not born either of your wife's mother nor of your wife's father—she is forbidden to you as long as your wife is living, and permitted to you after your wife is deceased, as it is written: <i>beside the other in her lifetime</i>. Marrying two true sisters is forbidden, regardless of whether either is alive or dead—not because of [the issue of being] a <i>rival</i> but rather because the two are <i>near kinswomen</i>, and any two women who are <i>near kinswomen</i> are forbidden forever to each other's husband, as it is written: <i>they are near kinswomen; it is lewdness</i> (Leviticus 18:17). But that which is written <i>a woman to her sister</i>, who is neither the daughter of her (= the man's wife's) father or mother, is forbidden to him because of <i>rival</i>. I have written what the Lord has informed us, so whoever does not comply will suffer the consequences.”<footnote id="223">Cf. Numbers 15:31.</footnote> And he ([= Qumisi) says before this: “<i>And a woman to her sister</i>—the sister referred to here is not the sister of your wife born from your wife's father or your wife's mother; rather, she is called the `sister of your wife' because she was born from your wife's father's wife by another man, as it is written: <i>The nakedness of thy father's wife's daughter, begotten of thy father, she is thy sister, thou shalt not uncover her nakedness</i> (Leviticus 18:11), and this is not referring to your biological sister, but one born from her father's wife or her mother's husband. From this you know that your wife's sister is forbidden to you during her lifetime and [after] her demise, for just as two brothers are forbidden to one woman in life and in death, so are two sisters forbidden forever [to one man] in life or in death. If a man dies, the deceased's wife is forbidden to his brothers; so too, if a woman dies, her husband is forbidden to the deceased's sisters. From this you know that two women who are <i>near kinswomen</i> to each other are forever forbidden to be wives of one husband, to both be [married] to the same man, whether in life or death, for this is lewdness and an abomination. This is written in connection with [marrying] a woman and her daughter, for they are <i>near kinswomen</i> to each other, as it is written: <i>they are near kinswomen; it is lewdness</i>. Therefore, two sisters are forbidden in life and in death, for it says: <i>they are near kinswomen</i>. They (= two sisters) in fact are closer kinswomen than a mother and her daughter for inheritance, estate, and clan—for with a woman and her daughter, one can be from the tribe of Reuben while the other is from the tribe of Simeon, whereas a woman and her sister [are always] born into the same tribe and the same clan, be it the father's or the mother's…”

<margin side="right">¶3.78.1</margin>Editor's Note: The Moses Çelebi Sinani mentioned here is Moses Çelebi Sinani the Second, as the list of years and generations will confirm (one should read Appendix V, “The Çelebi Family”).</quotation>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.79</margin>Now, R. Yefet the Physician b. Ẓaʿir, after citing these words of R. Daniel al-Qumisi in his aforementioned <i>Book of Commandments</i>, heaps great praise upon the wisdom of R. Daniel al-Qumisi, concluding as follows: “This is a very sharp investigation, which attests to the greatness of this enlightened man and his tremendous prowess. Let us ask our lofty Lord to place him in the Garden of Eden, and may we merit to be counted among his colleagues, Amen.” (See<i> Liqquṭé Qadmoniyyot</i> by the scholar R. Simḥa Pinsker, pp. 188–189.)</p>

<h1><margin side="right">¶3.80</margin>Appendix V (On the Çelebi Family)</h1>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.81</margin>In order for the reader to read our essay fluently<footnote id="224">These words, “for the reader to read our essay fluently,” are an allusion to Habakkuk 2:2. Babovich interlaced his entire Hebrew account of the Çelebi family with biblical words and phrases, which cannot be adequately or meaningfully rendered in English translation, and, accordingly, we have not noted the many references in the English. The interested reader should consult the Hebrew transcription for the full rhetorical effect.</footnote> and know who Moses Çelebi Sinani was, such that the sage Samuel Kohen b. R. Solomon Kohen of Damascus translated the <i>Book of Commandments</i> by R. Yefet the Physician ha-Ẓaʿir from Arabic into Hebrew in his honor, we see fit to mention the Çelebis here and say a few words about the history of this noble family.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.82</margin>The paterfamilias was a man named Sinan, the young officer<footnote id="225">The meaning of <i>ha-baḥur</i> is unclear. The translation relies on Babovich's use of the same term below in reference to his appointment to office at a young age.</footnote> and expert mason,<footnote id="226">The words translated as “mason” might mean “architect.”</footnote> son of Joseph the Officer (may God avenge his blood), who died in the year 5318 (1558<footnote id="226a">The original, published Hebrew and Arabic text of <i>Rosh Pinna</i> has the Hebrew year 5318 and provides a corresponding year of 1501. The Hebrew year 5318, however, corresponds to the year 1557 or 1558. In fact, Sinani died in 1557 or 1558, but arrived in the Crimea in 1501. See Philip E. Miller, <i>Karaite Separatism in Nineteenth-Century Russia: Joseph Solomon Lutski's Epistle of Israel's Deliverance</i> (Cincinnati: Hebrew Union College,1993) pp. 9-10. We have replaced 1501 with 1558 in both the Hebrew and Arabic texts in this edition.</footnote> CE) when he was 78 years old, who is known among the Karaites as “Sinan Baya Ḥuja.” He was a native of Persia. His ancestors were faithful officers of the Persian kings, and his father, R. Joseph the Officer, was especially beloved by the king, who raised him up and installed him above all his other officers. The other officers were jealous of him and libeled him to the king; the king believed their words and summarily sentenced him to death. He left behind a 13-year-old son named Sinan, because the Lord hid him, rescuing him from the sword of evil. Now it came to pass, at the end of seven years, that the falsity of the allegations made by R. Joseph the Officer's enemies was discovered, and the king greatly regretted the terrible deed that he had done. Therefore, to atone for his sin, he appointed the son of the unfairly executed [officer], Sinan the young man, to his father's seat, to be one of his officers, and he crowned him with glory and honor. However, Sinan the Officer remained in Persia only a short time; he was afraid to stay there, lest his father's fate befall him. He left for Crimea, the place of residence of his Karaite brethren. He was then 21 years of age. He appeared before the king of Crimea with a letter from the king of Persia, which praised Sinan's loyalty and talents. The king of Crimea, Khan Menjeli Giray, loved him, and he (= Sinan) served in a post in his palace during his reign and that of the next four kings. He was an expert mason, so the king appointed him overseer of the monumental construction of the marvelous royal palace, [which can still be seen] to this day in the city of Bakhchysarai, when the king moved his capital there from its original location in Iskhe Yurt. The construction of that palace was [underway] in the year 909 of the Muslim count, known as the “Hijri” [calendar], which corresponds to 1503 CE.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.83</margin>Sinan the Officer was a great benefactor to his Karaite brethren who dwelled in the city of [Chufut-]Kale, a half hour distant from Bakhchysarai. He helped to spread Torah study among them, and he opened new study houses for them. He settled wise teachers among them, who taught there under his supervision, and then the vine of Torah knowledge flourished there. May my God remember this for the good of this great man.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.84</margin>After Sinan, his son Joseph, the magnanimous<footnote id="227">The Hebrew word <i>gevir</i>, translated here as “magnanimous,” can also indicate wealth.</footnote> officer, served in his place. The latter died at age 79 in 1610.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.85</margin>After him came his son, Moses the magnanimous officer, who died at age 83 in 1665; he is Moses I.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.86</margin>After him came his son, Isaac the magnanimous officer, who died at age 66 in 1695.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.87</margin>After him came his son, Moses the magnanimous officer, who died at age 61 in 1726; he is Moses II.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.88</margin>It is he who is Moses Çelebi Sinani, in whose honor the <i>Book of Commandments</i> of R. Yefet the Physician ha-Ẓaʿir was translated, as we mentioned above. He, like all his ancestors, is buried in the graves of the holy [Chufut-]Kale. (See the book <i>Avné Zikkaron</i>, by the scholar and researcher R. Abraham Firkovich, p. 125, tombstone no. 429.)</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.89</margin>After him came his son, Isaac the magnanimous officer, who died at age 60 in 1756.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.90</margin>(See the aforementioned <i>Avné Zikkaron</i>, pp. 205–206.)</p>

<h1><margin side="right">¶3.91</margin>Appendix VI [On Ḥakham Mordecai b. Joseph Sultanski]</h1>

<p indent="no"><margin side="right">¶3.92</margin>We should note here that belief in the existence of angels was the subject of disagreement among the sages, including Karaite sages, until relatively recently.</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.93</margin>Note that Ḥakham Mordecai b. Joseph Sultanski (may his soul rest in Eden) (born in Lutzk, Poland in 1785 and died at a ripe old age in the city of Gozlov in Russian Crimea in 1878), in his book <i>Teṭiv Daʿat</i>, likewise rejects the existence of angels. He was taken to task for this by the sage and scholar Abraham Firkovich in one of his letters, which I have in my possession (scholars call it the <i>Iggeret Naḥash ʿAqalaton,</i> and he wrote it to his friend, the sage R. Moses Pampulov of blessed memory, father of the all-wise and famous Samuel Pampulov, may his soul rest in Eden).<footnote id="228">The parenthetical regarding <i>Iggeret Naḥash ʿAqalaton</i> appears in a footnote in the original Arabic publication of <i>Rosh Pinna</i>. In order to harmonize the Arabic and Hebrew, we have moved the footnote into the main Arabic text of paragraph 3.93 in our edition.</footnote> He heaps scorn upon him (= Sultanski), calling him “a rebellious elder who served in the High Priesthood for sixty years and then apostatized.”<footnote id="229">This refers to the Talmudic tale of the apostasy of Yoḥanan the High Priest, who, as the story goes, was a Pharisee until age 80, when he joined the Sadducees. Firkovich was in the habit of employing Talmudic references throughout his work.</footnote> From this Ḥakham Mordecai Sultanski (may his soul rest in Eden), we have a liturgical poem that begins: “My lover turned to his garden to see buds; had the vine flowered, were the pomegranates budding?” This is read on the day of <i>Shabbat ha-Gadol</i>, which is the Sabbath preceding the holiday of Passover (see the Siddur for the Holy Days).</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.94</margin>Here I have decided to add that Ḥakham Mordecai Sultanski was the father of my teacher and master Isaac Sultanski, the sage and distinguished preacher (may his soul rest in Eden), who died in Bakhchysarai in 1899 and is buried in the cemetery of the holy [Chufut-]Kale. I, a youngster, poured water over his hands<footnote id="230">That is, was a lowly disciple of his; cf. II Kings 3:11.</footnote> in Bakhchysarai from 1894 to 1897, and I completed my study of Karaite scholarship under his tutelage and served as his assistant. He laid his hands upon me,<footnote id="231">That is, “he ordained me.”</footnote> and I traveled to the city of Feodosia, where I became a teacher in the Karaite study hall. And so it was, in 1899, when the news reached Feodosia, my new residence, of the bitter tidings that my teacher and master had ascended in a storm to heaven, I traveled to Bakhchysarai and delivered a eulogy about him in the presence of a great gathering of friends and admirers of the departed, and in the presence of the <i>ḥakhamim</i> of the Karaite communities of nearby cities, who assembled to pay their final respects to the dearly departed. May God grant him complete reward in the eternal world for all his endeavors and actions in spreading Torah and wisdom among the Karaites, and may He fulfill upon him that which is written: <i>Light is sown for the righteous, and gladness for the upright in heart</i> (Psalms 97:11).</p>

<p><margin side="right">¶3.95</margin>From my teacher, Ḥakham Isaac Sultanski (may his soul rest in Eden), [there is] a translation of the <i>seliḥot</i> (penitential prayers) for Yom Kippur into the language of Qedar (= Tartaric), printed in the <i>siddur</i> for Yom Kippur (see the Vilna edition of Jacob Szyszman).</p>
</document>
